INSTRUCTOR: Over the past five years,
LLMs have achieved impressive results
and are now widely used, playing a key role
in the adoption of AI.
One reason is the enhanced human-AI communication.
Chatbots powered by LLMs provide human-like interactions.
LLMs produce very fluent, textual output,
creating the impression of generating original content that
is ready to use.
This creates a growing demand for AI
to operate across a wider range of applications.
However, no standalone monolithic AI model
is sufficient to solve all problems on its own.
For the next generation of AI, multiple models
should be integrated.
In this lecture, we will explore key aspects
of building AI systems that extend
beyond monolithic architectures.
Generative AI has become the primary approach
for AI-driven problem-solving.
For example, LLMs act as the core component
in AI systems development.
On the other hand, generative AI possess certain limitations
that restrict its applicability in many practical scenarios.
Here, we highlight some of the key limitations.
First, generative AI is computationally demanding.
For example, it is challenging to deploy
LLMs on local computers.
Even when LLMs are open and available to install locally,
they require supercomputers just to generate a response
to an input.
Moreover, training or extensively fine-tuning LLMs
is practically unfeasible for many users,
as it demands vast data and large-scale infrastructures.
This problem introduces significant limitations.
For example, in practical settings,
LLMs often rely on outdated information,
which can limit their applicability
in many real-world scenarios.
To optimize the performance of LLMs in practical applications,
we rely on the prompting process.
Although prompting can greatly enhance the performance of LLMs,
potentially mitigating some of the issues mentioned earlier,
it currently remains a manual ad hoc process.
LLMs excel in text analysis and generation.
But we need to combine them with other models
in applications that require analyzing
other types of information, such as images, videos, and drawings.
An additional concern is that LLMs often generate
inaccurate information, presenting it
in a convincing manner.
For example, they may provide incorrect dates
within an otherwise accurate and fluent description
of a historical event.
Identifying these inaccuracies is challenging, precisely
because LLMs are fluent, making their responses appear credible
even when incorrect.
This phenomenon, known as hallucination,
significantly limits the use of LLMs
in domains where information accuracy is critical.
On top of that, LLMs struggle with reasoning.
While they generate well-structured text,
they often fail when required to follow logical steps
to reach a decision.
Combined with their fluency, these reasoning errors
become difficult to detect, like hallucinations, making
them even more problematic.
This is one of the biggest challenges in AI
as we focus on the transition to trustworthy AI.
When using AI in high-risk applications,
such as medical diagnosis, where transparency and explainability
are required, AI reasoning with guarantees is a prerequisite.
For all these reasons, it is clear
that monolithic AI does not fit all.
Let's examine how we can combine different AI models.
Modern AI applications process multimedia data
in various forms collected from sensors, databases, reports,
the web, and other sources.
For example, in medical applications,
patient data may include biometric measurements,
diagnostic test results, MRIs, X-rays, EEGs,
and other medical records.
Additionally, domain knowledge is often available
and can be recorded in documents, papers,
or structured formats such as ontologies and rules.
This knowledge may include health system reports,
clinical guidelines, standardized terminologies,
regulations, scientific publications,
and other domain-specific resources.
Different types of AI models are trained, adapted, developed,
and deployed based on this data, depending
on the type of data and the specific tasks
the models need to perform.
For example, LLMs are used for text analysis and production.
Deep neural networks are used for image and video analysis.
Symbolic AI engines are used for knowledge-based data analysis
and reasoning.
The different characteristics of AI models
are useful in practice.
LLMs dramatically improve human-AI interaction,
for example in collaboration with doctors
in medical diagnosis support systems.
Symbolic AI systems can address challenges
related to the interpretability of deep neural networks
and the integration of up-to-date knowledge
into AI applications, and so on.
For this reason, the focus is on AI systems
that combine AI models creating hybrid systems that
leverage the strengths of multiple methodologies.
In this way, AI systems can now handle tasks
closer to human capabilities, expanding
the scope of AI applications.
To enhance the integration of multiple AI models,
many services should be automated.
For example, search and retrieval
allows for contextual understanding
and the aggregation of up-to-date information.
Prompt engineering enhances the performance and reliability
of LLMs.
AI reasoning may provide explanations,
detect hallucinations, and verify
the correctness of AI models.
Automating these services that work
as intermediates facilitates AI model integration.
For example, prompt engineering can
leverage up-to-date knowledge retrieved
from using search and retrieval, while symbolic AI can
help detect and control hallucinations of LLM models.
Image analysis using deep neural networks
can expand the context when prompting LLMs,
adding images as input in addition to texts.
There are plenty of ways to combine AI models, given
the specific needs of its application,
helping us in the AI paradigm shift, the transition
from monolithic AI systems to multicomponent or compound
AI systems.
Many AI systems in practical use today are not standalone.
They consist of multiple integrated components.
Sometimes they are based on LLMs incorporating
additional features.
In fact, many of these features have become so integrated
that most users assume they are an inherent part of LLM
functionality.
An example is Retrieval Augmented Generation, RAG.
In RAG, automated retrieval services
gather relevant documents and use
them to enhance the user query before prompting
generative models.
This enables LLMs to incorporate domain-specific and up-to-date
information into their responses.
Systems like ChatGPT utilize web search to enhance context
and provide more relevant and up-to-date responses.
RAG techniques have advanced significantly
and are now implemented in most commercial AI systems.
We also observed that modern commercial LLM-based systems
feature multimodal capabilities.
For example, they can process images as input,
incorporate generative models for multimedia content,
or connect to devices like mobile phones
to accept video input.
Additionally, they incorporate consistency-checking mechanism
by leveraging formal knowledge representation
and automated reasoning systems to ensure the reliability
of their results.
This integration leads to neurosymbolic AI systems
which combine the strengths of the two
main pillars of Al development-- machine
learning and symbolic AI.
Several methodologies for automating and optimizing
the integration of multiple AI components
have been proposed-- for example, compound AI.