INSTRUCTOR: Most people believe that artificial intelligence
is powerful and risky at the same time.
So ensuring AI trust and, by extension, AI transparency
is key.
From model training to decision making,
it is important to provide explanations
of how the AI system works.
Explaining AI systems can be challenging.
The right form of explanations depend on the context.
Explanations should be intuitive in the sense
that humans should be able to understand it.
At the same time, explanations should be accurate in the sense
that they should ensure that AI systems
operation is transparent.
By addressing these challenges, we
can move towards responsible, interpretable,
and human-centered AI.
In this lecture, we will discuss the need for explainable AI,
its main challenges, and the technologies that support it.
Starting with the usefulness of AI and its main risks,
we will explore the challenges of providing explanations
that are both intuitive and accurate.
Next, we will outline the taxonomy
of methods for explainable AI, providing examples
and highlighting the key concepts
behind widely used approaches.
AI is changing the way we work every day.
We use AI to automate repetitive, sometimes
tedious tasks in various domains or to assist humans
in complex decision making.
In health care, AI is becoming increasingly prominent.
For example, AI-driven tools assist doctors
in detecting diseases with greater precision
or speed up drug discovery, reducing the time and cost
of developing new medications.
In manufacturing, AI is now a game changer.
AI robots dramatically improve repetitive tasks like assembly,
disassembly, and packaging.
AI-automated quality control systems
can quickly and efficiently detect defects,
improving product quality.
In education, AI is creating new learning experiences,
making education more accessible and
adaptable to individual needs.
AI-based technological innovations like gamification,
virtual reality, chatbots, generative AI, et cetera,
equip educators with powerful tools.
AI also plays a crucial role in culture,
enhancing preservation, accessibility, and creativity.
Users engage with cultural content
in more immersive and interactive ways
through AI technologies.
Creators are empowered by AI tools, including generative AI.
AI is also highly anticipated to play an important role
in sustainability and climate change,
helping scientists analyze vast amounts of data
to forecast climate conditions, track ecological changes,
deforestation, wildlife population shifts, and pollution
levels.
Besides its usefulness, AI also comes
with risks that can cause both material and immaterial harm
to people.
For instance, failures in autonomous vehicles
can lead to accidents.
Misdiagnosing medical conditions may result in adverse health
outcomes for patients.
Breakdowns in industrial automation
can lead to workplace accidents.
Failures in algorithmic trading or mistakes in logistics
can cause financial losses.
AI-generated deepfakes can impersonate individuals carrying
out unauthorized transactions.
AI can also cause immaterial harm.
Notably, AI poses significant risks
to personal data protection and privacy.
AI-powered behavior tracking systems
can be exploited for mass surveillance
without control, violating individuals' privacy rights.
AI's ability to interconnect data from across the web
can potentially lead to de-anonymization of individuals
and the exposure of sensitive personal information.
There are also major concerns related
to discrimination and fairness.
Bias in training data can lead to discrimination
against certain genders, ethnicities, or age groups.
AI-driven medical and financial services
may have reduced accuracy for specific demographic groups,
resulting in unequal access to care or financial opportunities.
These risks and potential implications associated with AI
contribute to a lack of trust in its use and recommendations.
On top of the existing risks, speculative ideas
such as human-like AI robots with
artificial superintelligence raise concerns
that machines could one day surpass humans.
As a result, end users, especially experts
such as medical practitioners, often
hesitate to trust AI recommendations even
in scenarios where they achieve greater performance
than human decision makers.
This phenomenon, known as algorithmic aversion,
significantly undermines human AI collaboration.
The only way to enhance AI excellence, usefulness,
and trust is to promote AI technologies that
ensure transparency, fairness, and accountability.
To this end, we should train models
on well-balanced and diverse data sets
to minimize biases and evaluate models
for potential gender, racial, or socioeconomic biases.
Moreover, AI systems should offer clear insights
into how they get to their conclusions.
Ideally, we should be able to understand the reasons
behind model predictions so that we are able to validate them.
The compliance to regulatory frameworks for AI
plays an important role, providing guarantees.
To reduce potential risks and build trust,
organizations utilizing AI technologies
should implement guidelines, standards,
or regulatory frameworks.
Technical services that validate compliance
with these regulations should be developed.
Based on these technical services,
high-risk AI systems used in practice,
like AI-assisted medical diagnosis systems,
should provide guarantees for compliance
with the AI regulatory framework.