INSTRUCTOR: Let's describe a simple example,
a movie recommender that gathers and analyzes relevant data
and knowledge from the web.
Through the web, we can access relevant information
that can prove highly valuable for this app.
For example, a Google search for La La Land
retrieves over 4 billion results.
This vast pool of information is indeed rich,
but it also contains a considerable amount
of redundancy.
It's interesting that the data is presented by Google
in a structured format.
This means that the search engine
uses some type of semantics to organize the presentation
of the results accordingly.
Concerning the type of the retrieved data,
we see structured data about the movie,
like title, genre, director, actors, awards, et cetera.
We also see unstructured data, like text, audio, images,
or video.
Examples include movie synopsis, scripts, audio clips, trailers,
photos, soundtracks, and more.
In addition, meta information about the movie--
examples are ratings, reviews, and critics' assessments.
Finally, some user-oriented information,
like the user's viewing history, preferences,
likes, and dislikes.
Using AI services, the movie recommender
should view this diverse array of information
as a virtual database containing an exceptionally
rich and multifaceted relevant information,
especially if we see this information as entity
descriptions rather than sets of words.
Symbolic AI focuses on the use of symbols and rules
to represent and manipulate knowledge.
The goal is to emulate the way humans solve
problems using logical representations and reasoning.
The first challenge is the semantic data description
that involves understanding and representing
data in a semantically rich format using formal semantics
like common understandable names and references to domain
terminology.
This involves the process of making data more meaningful
and machine understandable by associations
with knowledge and context.
This allows the capture of underlying data meaning,
making it more valuable for decision-making.
In our example, given the data and terminology,
we can associate terms from the terminology with the schema
of data sources.
The goal is to consume data terminologies
and their associations-- here, for example,
data from IMDb and terminology from schema.org or DBpedia.org--
and produce useful statements with intuitive explicit meaning,
like has director, La La Land, Damien Chazelle;
and has author, La La Land, Damien Chazelle.
Sometimes we find the same information
in different data sources, for example in IMDb and Wikipedia.
Semantic data integration technologies
can help us combine and unify data.
This is important since in order to make decisions,
we first need to harmonize and interrelate
data from different sources to enrich it.
In this example, these formal statements
represents information collected from IMDb and Wikipedia.
The next step is to build technologies
to see the vast amount of big, heterogeneous data
as a single database and gather information based
on the meaning of the data.
This refers to the ability to pose possibly complex questions
to a large and diverse set of data
and get meaningful, context-sensitive answers.
In this example, using semantic data representation and data
integration, we can gather information
about the genre of the movie, its director, release date,
and production country.
When analyzing data from different sources,
we may reach conclusions that are
based on common knowledge of the domain using reasoning.
For example, it is evident that every romantic musical film
is also a romantic film.
And every romantic film is a love story.
Taking into account this domain knowledge and the fact
that La La Land is a romantic musical film,
we can infer that La La Land is a love story, even if it is not
explicitly stated.
This is particularly important in cases
that the recommender tries to retrieve love stories.
Here, we understand that only through reasoning,
we can infer that La La Land is a love story
and give this information to the recommender.
Symbolic AI technologies can help
to automate this human ability and possibly
enrich data by making explicit some implicit information.
This is the goal of automated reasoning, which
involves the use of computational methods
to draw inferences by making logical deductions.