INSTRUCTOR: Now for the final part,
we're going to talk about the key takeaways from today's
recitation.
What did we learn today?
First of all, we learned that prompt engineering helps
guide and shape how language models respond,
and even small tweaks and changes in the prompt
can actually have a big effect on the output.
We show that there are multiple types of prompting,
including zero-shot, few-shot, and chain-of-thought, each
with different strengths.
We also saw other types of prompting,
but these were the first ones we examined
and some of the most usual ones.
We also saw that the role and style instructions
let us control the tone and persona of the model output.
And then we talked about Retrieval-Augmented Generation,
which improves accuracy by grounding responses
in real documents that we can provide to the models.
And as we saw, prompt chaining in combination with RAG
can make language models more trustworthy for complex tasks
like medical question answering.
And by prompt chaining, I remind you,
we mean the concept of providing smaller prompts step by step
to our LLM instead of bombarding it
with a single large prompt that contains
every task we want it to do.