INSTRUCTOR: We start with logistic regression.
Logistic regression is a linear model.
It's quite transparent.
Because at the end, we get, for each feature,
a certain coefficient.
And it's very easy to interpret these coefficients
because if the coefficient is positive,
it increases the probability of label 1.
So if a feature has a very positive coefficient,
this means that it contributes a lot to predicting someone
as having the label 1.
If the coefficient is negative, it decreases this chance.
So we define our logistic regression pipeline here.
First, we have the preprocess step,
and then we have the classifier, the logistic regression.
We fit the model on our training set.
And then we are going to print the coefficients to basically
see how each feature contributes to the final prediction.
We can see we have ranked the features here with in descending
order, basically.
And as you can see, the factor, the feature
with the highest positive coefficient is marital status.
What does this mean?
It means that people that are married, according to the model,
are more likely to have income above 50k.
Also, if someone has a capital gain,
this is also a very strong predictor.
So you would say that these two are the features with the two
highest coefficients.
So we can extract the interpretability.
Like, we can extract basically the information
that, as far as interpretability is concerned for this model,
the most important features are the marital status
and the capital gain.
And then all factors contribute positively,
which means that the higher, for example, the education level,
the more it contributes to a positive income.
But the two highest ones were these two, the marital status
and capital gain.
Another type of classifier is decision trees.
Decision trees basically produce some logical rules that
are very easy to visualize.
And they are extremely interpretable.
We are defining this preprocessing here.
Here, we do not need to scale our features
in the preprocessing because it doesn't affect the model,
and we want the split to be intuitive.
So we want the features to have their natural--
meaning their natural quantities without us altering them.
So we define the tree pipeline, and we fit on the training set.
Now we're going to visualize the tree,
and we are going to see how easy it is to get interpretability
from tree models.
We visualize-- we print the tree.
And it's very easy to read it.
For example, here, we have the following.
If the marital status is less than 0.5-- and as I remind you,
marital status is either 0 or 1.
So basically, if the marital status is equal to 0,
so if someone is unmarried, basically,
but they have a capital gain that is, say, above 7,000,
then we end up here in this node,
which predicts that this person has an income of above 50k.
I repeat, the way we read the tree is,
we ask the question in the first row,
is the marital status less than 0.5?
If this is true, we go left.
If this is false, we go right.
So in the case that we go left, we end up in this node here.
And then we ask this question.
Is the capital gain less than 7,000?
If yes, we go here.
If no, we go here.
Here, on the right, if someone is married and, for example,
if the education number is less than 12.5, we go left.
But if it's above, which means that they're
highly educated and married, goes right.
Here, we predict that the people have an income of above 50k,
which intuitively makes sense as factors,
and it's as easy to be completely transparent and see
what the model decides for each sample.
For example, for the first point of the test set,
if we pass it through the tree, we
can basically see in which nodes the sample falls into,
which path it follows to reach a final leaf node.
So we can see the exact path and understand
why this prediction was made.
Now, logistic regression and decision trees
are interpretable models.
That's why they are still fairly popular.
They were always easy to use.
But they are not very powerful in terms of modeling.
Ensemble models, like random forests and XGBoost,
that you have probably seen in other modules are more accurate.
But they are ensemble of decision trees.
And they work in different ways.
We're not going to go into details
about what the differences are between the two.
But what is important to remember
is that they are ensembles of many different trees.
So it's much harder to recover why a prediction was
made since there are averages or hierarchies of models
inside each of these ensemble classifiers.
We define our random forest pipeline,
and we fit on the training set.
And we also define our XGBoost pipeline,
and we also fit on the training set.
Now let's see how we can get an idea
about proxies for interpretability
in these models.
One way is to extract the feature importances.
Feature importance ranks variables
according to how useful and important
they are for prediction.
This is a global explanation.
Global means that it describes the model behavior
across all samples.
It is not input specific.
For example, for the random forest, after we run the model,
we can access the feature importances
very easily using this feature importances quantity.
And we can print a data frame that shows the feature
name and the importance.
Roughly, the feature importance is
computed in the following way.
For each feature, every time the feature is used in a split,
we measure how much the split reduces the impurity,
so how much it improves the prediction in some sense.
So we sum these impurity reductions
across all of the trees for each feature.
And then we normalize the values so they add up to 1.
And this results in mean decrease in impurity.
And of course, the higher the value, the more informative
the feature is across all of the trees of the model.
Here, for the random forest, the most important feature
appears to be age, second, marital status, and third,
the education number.
What's interesting is that across all the models,
we won't get the same top features
in terms of how informative they are,
which is interesting because they don't all
work in the same way.
So they might reveal different important factors
based on each model's way of being trained.
A problem that arises with these feature importances,
for example, for random forest, is that, OK,
we show which feature is important.
But how does this feature contribute
its important, and what's the direction of influence?
If the age is large, does this contribute
to a higher probability of having
a large income or a lower?
We assume, based on what we've seen
with the rest of the models, that it must
lead to higher probability.
But feature importances do not show that.
And, actually, this example is very intuitive,
so we kind of expect how each feature would contribute.
But it's not always the case when
we are dealing with more complex data sets.
So this is a limitation of the feature importance part.
Now a very useful explainability tool
that is used a lot with XGBoost models is the SHAP values.
SHAP stands for Shapley additive explanations
and basically assigns each feature
a value representing how much it contributes
to a given prediction.
It's fairly complicated to calculate the SHAP value.
But the intuition behind it is that for each feature,
we consider all possible combinations of other features
and ask how much adding the feature changes the prediction.
And we average this contribution across all the combinations.
We are going to see how we visualize the SHAP values
and how we can read the plot.
But basically, the idea is that on the y-axis,
we have the features sorted by importance.
And in the x-axis, we have the SHAP value.
A positive SHAP value corresponds
to pushing the model toward predicting the positive class,
and the negative SHAP value pushes the model
towards the negative class.
And the color is also important here for the original feature
value.
Red means that the feature has a high value.
And blue, it means that it has a low value.
I know that it sounds a lot, but we're going to see an example,
and we can explain how this looks like there.
This is how the subplot looks like.
Let's try to decode what's happening here.
On the y-axis, you can see all of
the features-- marital status, age,
education number, et cetera.
They are ranked in decreasing order of importance.
So the highest is the one with highest importance as well.
These blue and red dots that you see here actually correspond
to the actual sample.
So each bullet point here is one sample of our data set.
Now, everything that lies on the right side of the x-axis
contributes to the model having a positive value,
having a higher probability of predicting the positive value--
and on the left, the opposite.
So marital status, for example, has--
as a feature, there are a lot of points that contribute
to towards the right side.
And this happens-- all these features
that are here have a high value of the feature.
So red corresponds to the value of marital status.
And blue corresponds to the value of marital status.
So this tells us that these samples here
had a high marital status value because they are red.
And high marital status value is mapped
on the right side of the x-axis, which means
that it contributes positively.
So a high marital status contributes positively.
High marital status is equal to 1
now-- contributes positively to the final prediction being 1,
being high.
On the other hand, there are a lot
of samples that go towards the negative side, towards 0.
And all of these samples have a low value of marital status.
So this means that when marital status is 0,
this tends to mean that the prediction is going to be 0.
Similarly here, for example, education number--
all the samples that are on the right side
that push towards the prediction equals 1 have high values.
So high education number means higher probability
of predicting 1.
Low education number means higher probability
of predicting class 0.
So this is the way of reading this diagram.
And what's good about SHAP values
is that you can see not just which feature is most important
but also what's the direction of contribution,
unlike the feature importances.
Because here, we saw not just that the marital status
is the most important feature, but that the marital status
leads to higher prediction of class 1.
Last thing about SHAP values is that they constitute
a local explainability method because we are looking
at each point separately, where exactly it lies,
and how important each part of this point is.
But since then we can visualize across all of the points what
happens, this reveals also some more global sense
of interpretability, of explainability,
some global understanding of how features contribute on average
to the final predictions.