INSTRUCTOR: The performance of AI systems, in particular, of LLMs,
is closely related to how questions
are formulated, meaning the input provided to the model.
The automation of prompting in AI systems
with multiple components is a key element.
Rather than relying on manual prompting,
automated techniques allow AI to generate
dynamic and optimized interactions,
improving efficiency and adaptability.
Let's examine the prompting process
in more detail, focusing on LLM prompting, which
is both the most complex and has a significant impact
on system performance.
Prompting is actually a black-box style communication
with a model.
Consider, for example, that we can prompt
an LLM to compose a poem.
We just tell the LLM, "Write a short poem about the blue sea."
The model then generates a poem as output.
So a prompt is the input to the generative AI model that defines
the task to be performed.
Prompt engineering is the process
of crafting a prompt to optimize the LLM's response.
This optimization involves structuring
the prompt to include necessary information and context,
enabling the LLM to generate a precise and accurate response.
The prompt is represented in various formats,
depending on the type of the prompt model.
For example, we can provide text, an image, a video, audio,
a multimedia file, or a combination of these as input
and request a corresponding text, image, video,
or other format as output.
The type of prompt can also vary.
For example, it can be a short statement, a command,
an evaluation, or a detailed prompt that
includes context descriptions, example references,
and specific instructions.
The goal of the prompt can also vary
depending on the phases of the interaction with the AI system.
For example, we can request information
to establish context describing the style of the desired
response, provide feedback to the AI system,
offer methodological guidance by outlining appropriate steps,
or ask for explanations and reasoning
behind the AI's response.
There are numerous examples of the above, such as the prompt,
"Write a short poem about the blue sea,"
where we request the generation of a text,
or, "What is a Turing Award?"
with which we request information,
or, "Write this as a native English speaker,"
with which we specify the style of the generated text.
Let's now explore some techniques
used in prompt engineering.
One of the core techniques is motivated by important findings
from the analysis of LLM performance,
particularly of the larger models.
These findings show that LLMs can adjust their output based
on examples provided in the input,
allowing them to adapt to different patterns.
This process is known as in-context learning.
For example, a prompt designed to assess
the likelihood of pneumonia could
list symptoms and request yes-or-no answer,
along with a brief explanation.
This prompt is called zero-shot learning
because the model is given only the instruction
without any example.
On the other hand, we can provide
the model with labeled examples before asking
to classify a new input.
This technique is known as few-shot learning.
In this example, before requesting an estimate,
pneumonia or not, we first provide a similar example
where the right answer is already known and given
to the LLM.
In this case, the LLM sticks to a specific form of the answer
while taking into account the ideal reasoning,
linking symptoms to a diagnosis.
In-context learning has been shown
to be highly effective in practice, significantly
enhancing the performance of LLMs.
Moreover, we can automate the construction
of in-context learning prompts using semantic search and data
retrieval to retrieve appropriate examples.
Another powerful prompting technique
which significantly enhances results
is chain-of-thought prompting.
If we know the reasoning process required
to derive a complex result or conclusion,
it is highly effective to explicitly include it
in the prompt.
In the pneumonia example mentioned earlier,
we can provide the key reasoning steps involved in diagnosis
and/or specify the sequence of information
we want the LLM's response to follow.
In this case, we can also request
a detailed response that follows the specified reasoning steps.
The chain-of-thought technique, when
combined with in-context learning,
has proven to be one of the most effective approaches
for addressing LLMs' hallucination issues
and reducing LLMs' errors in arithmetic operations
or reasoning tasks.
To do this, we provide examples that
include detail, step-by-step execution of operations,
or the logical sequence of conclusions being drawn.
This chain-of-thought concept can be expanded even further
involving the LLM.
Provide multiple prompts sequentially,
guiding the LLM through a structured reasoning process.
Each prompt refines or builds upon the previous response,
gradually improving accuracy and coherence.
This technique is known as prompt chaining.
In the pneumonia example mentioned earlier,
we can first ask the LLM to identify relevant symptoms
before proceeding with the assessment prompt.
Here, for example, the LLM's response
may include symptoms such as persistent cough or shortness
of breath as indicative signs of pneumonia.
Based on this response, we can ask
the LLM to assess the likelihood of pneumonia given the presence
of some of these symptoms.
The prompt-chaining technique can be applied dynamically
during user interaction, allowing
for adaptive and context-aware responses.
In this example, the LLM can generate specific questions
for the user, allowing us to gather
additional relevant information for a more informed response.
Beyond these fundamental prompting techniques,
many additional methods enhance prompt engineering services,
enabling automation and significantly improving
the performance of AI systems.
Moreover, during the prompt engineering process,
additional AI services, such as semantic search and retrieval
or automated reasoning, can be used
to gather the necessary information,
incorporate domain knowledge, verify LLM responses
for obvious errors, and enhance accuracy and reliability.
Another technique used in prompt engineering
is based on prompt templates.
Specifically, well-crafted, high-quality prompt templates
are developed for each prompt structure
and stored in a database for reuse.
Then specific templates can be selected and, if needed,
combined and modified accordingly.
Finally, based on domain knowledge, context,
and relevant user-specific information,
templates are customized to generate the appropriate prompt
for each specific case.
For example, if we decide to apply the chain-of-thought
technique, instead of using the simple prompt,
"Does the chest X-ray show signs of pneumonia?"
we do the following.
We find, from the available chain-of-thought prompt
templates, a suitable one which is
relevant to medical diagnosis based on imaging.
Based on the specific scenario, we replace image type
with chest X-ray, label with lung opacity, and so on,
customizing the template.
In this way, we construct a detailed chain-of-thought
prompt.
These are methodologies that take an even more systematic
approach by utilizing optimization algorithms
to refine and enhance prompt generation.
Using a score function, optimal prompts
can be determined using algorithms
like reinforcement learning, genetic search, gradient-based,
or Bayesian optimization.