INSTRUCTOR: Let's now discuss
the key methods for explaining AI predictions,
categorized under the broader field of explainable AI.
We can classify explainability methods
into two broad categories.
The straightforward approach is to use models that
are inherently interpretable.
Examples include linear regression
and logistic regression, which offer direct interpretability
through model coefficients, decision trees and rule fit,
which provide decision pathways that humans can follow,
or naive Bayes classifiers, which bases predictions
on transparent probabilistic reasoning, K-Nearest
Neighbor, KNN, which classifies based
on proximity to known examples.
While these models are easier to understand,
they may not always achieve the best performance
for complex tasks.
For black-box models such as deep neural networks
and ensemble methods, post hoc explanation techniques
are essential.
These techniques analyze and explain
model behavior after training without modifying
the model itself.
There are three key types of post hoc explanations.
The first is the global explanation methods.
These methods aim to explain how a model makes
decisions across all instances.
Examples include feature importance methods,
which rank input features based on their contribution
to the model's output, and surrogate models, where
we approximate a complex model using an interpretable one.
The second type is the local explanation methods.
Here, instead of explaining the entire model,
local methods focus on the individual predictions.
Examples include methods that generate
simplified, interpretable models for specific instances
or methods that highlight which parts of the input an image,
for instance, influenced a neural network's decision.
And finally, the third type is the counterfactual explanations.
Rather than describing why a prediction was made,
counterfactuals answer what-if questions.
For instance, if the income of a loan applicant
were increased by 10%, would the model approve the loan?
These explanations are particularly
useful for decision-making scenarios
where specific actions are implemented to improve outcomes.
To summarize, interpretable models
can offer building transparency.
But for complex AI systems, post hoc methods
such as global explanations, local decision interpretations,
and counterfactuals are essential to build trust.
Let's now look at key concepts behind interpretable models,
focusing on decision trees, one of the most transparent machine
learning models.
Decision trees offer a structured way
to understand predictions, and we
can leverage them in many ways to extract explanations.
Here is a binary classification problem
and a simple decision tree predictor
with two features-- x1 and x2.
One of the simplest and most intuitive ways
to interpret a decision tree is by extracting rules
from each structure.
Each path from the root to a leaf node
represents a set of conditions that lead to a prediction.
These paths can be rewritten as if-then rules,
making the model's decision-making process
explicit.
Here, we can see that two different paths
lead to a green leaf node.
So the rule if x2 less than 3, et cetera, then green
is an explanation of the trained classifier.
Another way to interpret decision trees
is by analyzing feature importance.
The importance of a feature is determined
by how often it is used for splitting
and how much it contributes to reducing uncertainty
in the data set.
To compute this, we first identify all nodes where a given
feature is used, then measure the information gain or variance
reduction each time it appears.
And finally, aggregate these values across the tree
to quantify the feature's influence.
It's more challenging to calculate,
but if we apply this to our example,
we'll discover that both features are crucial.
Another explanation technique is to decompose the decision paths.
For instance, specific explanations,
we can decompose the decision path
followed by a particular input.
Instead of looking at the entire tree,
we analyze the specific sequence of splits leading
to the final prediction.
At each decision node, we examine the feature's
contribution and how it influences the probability
of the final class.
This method breaks down the prediction
into interpretable steps, making it easier to justify
and debug individual decisions.
In our example, we can observe that x1 greater than 4
always means red.
This provides a global explanation,
helping us understand which features
have the greatest impact on the model's overall decision-making.
The above techniques make decision trees
one of the most interpretable models providing transparency
while maintaining strong predictive power.
While decision trees are known for their transparency,
it's important to recognize their limitations
in interpretability.
Decision trees are easier to understand when they are small,
typically when they have a limited number of splits.
But larger trees are more complex,
making rule extraction impractical.
For instance, a tree with just 10 to 15 levels
can have thousands of decision paths,
making it as opaque as a neural network model.
Moreover, decision trees are highly
sensitive to data set variations, which can
lead to unstable explanations.
This highlights the trade-off between complexity
and explainability.
And it is the main reason why carefully designing
decision trees for interpretability
is so important.