INSTRUCTOR: Now let's explore how inference algorithms
can automatically process semantic data and knowledge,
uncovering additional information that is implicitly
contained within them.
Let's begin with the formal representation
of the information explicitly stated
in the first sentence of our example description.
Specifically, a set of facts is represented
in the form of triples.
These structure representations are
referred to as the semantic data of our description.
Besides representing them as triples,
we can also visualize them as a graph, which is often
more intuitive for humans, especially when dealing
with small-scale semantic descriptions.
Additionally, we can define terminological knowledge
that describes the domain in a structured manner.
This knowledge can include axioms
that define concept hierarchies and axioms that
describe relationships between concepts within the domain.
Finally, we can examine the formal representation
of this knowledge in RDF format, specifically
using the Turtle file format.
Every Turtle file can be read by machines
and represented in the form of triples or as a graph.
Here, we can observe that this RDF specification utilizes
URIs from well-known terminologies,
such as DBpedia and schema.org.
Now let's explore how a symbolic reasoner operates
processing knowledge.
It takes as input the knowledge we previously examined,
which serves as the formal description of the domain,
operating in various ways.
First, it can verify whether the given knowledge is consistent.
Second, it can take a property that certain entities may
possess and return the entities in the knowledge base
that satisfy it.
Moreover, it can evaluate a hypothesis
for a specific entity or a specific property
and determine whether it holds or not.
Or it can verify whether two entities are connected
by a specific relationship.
All these tasks, and many more, are automated reasoning problems
that symbolic AI reasoners can accurately solve.
Let's see a specific example.
The reasoner takes the following question as input.
Is La La Land a love story?
And answers yes or no.
If the assumption is La La Land love story is
an explicit fact of the knowledge base,
then the answer is obviously yes.
If not, we must follow a sequence of systematic steps
that correspond to rigorous reasoning
processes to ensure accuracy.
These processes may involve one or more facts
combined with one or more rules from the knowledge base.
To ensure guarantees, the conclusions
must be logically sound and self-evident.
In other words, a sequence of deriving logically evident
conclusions can ultimately lead to a final conclusion that
may not look obvious at first, just like in human reasoning.
In our example, the first step involves a specific fact
and a rule.
In this case, the fact is La La Land is a romantic musical film.
And the rule is all romantic musical films
are romantic films.
Their combination leads to an obvious conclusion.
La La Land is a romantic film.
This conclusion represents a fact
that is implied by the knowledge,
although it is not explicitly stated.
Since this is a logically sound conclusion,
we can now insert it, expanding our knowledge base.
In the second step, we follow a similar process.
We use again a fact and a rule, but the fact now
is the one that we added in the previous step.
So we now know that La La Land is a romantic film.
And thus from the rule all romantic films are love stories,
the obvious conclusion is that La La Land is a love story.
This conclusion not only expands our knowledge base
but is also the answer to the question under consideration.
Let's now recap and generalize the process.
Reasoners derive new knowledge out of existing ones,
making implicit knowledge explicit.
To do this, they apply knowledge derivation rules,
many times the conclusions of which are logically
sound and self-evident.
The rule applied in both steps of our example
is intuitive and logically sound.
If an entity x has a property a and the property a implies
a property b, then the entity x has the property b.
This is a version of a well-known and widely used
logical implication rule called modus ponens.
A similar logical implication rule
can be applied to extend knowledge graphs.
In this case, we are looking for a subgraph pattern, where
a node x has an is-a successor.
That is a.
Then the rule a gives b can be applied and add an is-a edge
from the node x to the node b.
This implication process is referred to as materialization.
Through the process of materialization,
knowledge graphs can be expanded by adding logically inferred
information, ensuring that the newly incorporated data remains
correct and consistent.
For example, by applying the materialization rule
we discussed in the example knowledge graph,
in the first step, we can add an edge between the node La La Land
and the node Romantic Film.
In the second step, we can similarly
add an edge between the La La Land node and the Love Story
node.
These materialization rules are not
the only ones that can be applied
for the logical expansion of knowledge graphs.
We can define many more knowledge derivation rules
based on logical inference to further expand
and enrich knowledge graphs.
For example, beyond the simple extension rule
that led us to add an edge between the La La Land
node and the Love Story node, as previously demonstrated,
we can define a rule that links the relationship
between a node x and a node y with a property
that belongs to node y rather than node x,
as in the previous case.
As an example, consider the implication rule
that connects the has directed relation of a node x
with a node y with a categorization of y to director.
This seems obvious, and if we apply this implication rule
to the fact La La Land has director Damien Chazelle,
we get the conclusion that Damien Chazelle is a director,
not explicit in the knowledge graph--
intuitive and useful.
There are additional materialization rules
that are less obvious.
For example, some relations may be transitive.
This means that if a node x has a nar successor y and this nar
successor has a nar successor z, then z
should be also an nar successor of x.
This implication rule may be extremely useful in practice,
especially when considering relations
that have this property.
And there are plenty of them.
As an example, consider the class-classmate relation.
We read in the Wikipedia description of La La Land
that Damien Chazelle, author and director of La La Land,
was a classmate of Justin Hurwitz that scored La La
Land at Harvard University.
It is reasonable to assume that a classmate of Justin Hurwitz
is also a classmate of Damien Chazelle.
This is a materialization of the knowledge graph
that makes sense.
On the other hand, there is a tricky point here.
Of course, there are many classmates of Justin Hurwitz.
Naming and introducing the knowledge graph, some of them,
and applying the transitivity implication rule,
we may come up with many implied relationships.
This is an example why reasoning is a challenging problem.
Summarizing, although many knowledge derivation rules
can be applied in practice, and all of them
may be useful in some use-case scenarios,
sometimes there are many irrelevant conclusions
that can be derived from knowledge bases
using these implication rules.
This can make the reasoning problem
unnecessarily impractical.
This is the reason why symbolic AI
reasoners should be selective.
Sophisticated automated reasoning algorithms
for knowledge graphs should materialize
only useful conclusions given the user query.
The good news here is that there are
many scalable, sophisticated reasoning services that
can be used in practice to support knowledge graph
expansion and be used in real-life applications.
So what is the take-home message of this lecture?
First, symbolic AI can be leveraged to represent
semantic data and encode domain knowledge
in a structured and interpretable manner.
Second, with symbolic AI, we can efficiently access
and analyze relevant data based on services
like data semantification, data integration, data enrichment, et
cetera.
Third, there are various successful methods, standards,
and tools for representing data and knowledge on the web.
Specifically, these tools and standards
facilitate the naming, categorization,
and interrelation of entities on the web,
enabling domain descriptions that are both accessible
and machine understandable.
Fourth, symbolic AI reasoners can transform implicit knowledge
into explicit knowledge, making hidden relationships
and logical conclusions computationally accessible.
And the last message--
automated reasoning is a challenging problem.
We should be selective and employ sophisticated strategies
to prevent the materialization of trivial or irrelevant
knowledge.
And this ends the presentation.
Thanks for watching.