INSTRUCTOR: Now for the third and last section
of the recitation, we're going to take
a brief look at how language interpretability looks like.
So we will take a look at attention heatmaps
and lime for text.
We're going to use the DistilBERT model.
This is a BERT type of model.
It's small and which we did on purpose for educational reasons
here.
And we are going to take this input sentence.
I absolutely loved the cinematography,
but the plot was terrible.
We are going to tokenize this sentence.
So basically, break this sentence
into smaller words or subwords that
maps these parts in certain IDs that are readable by the model.
We pass the inputs through the model we have already loaded,
and in the output, we get probabilities
about the sentiment that we are predicting.
So basically, after loading the model,
we want to see-- we will run an example
sentence through the model.
And we want to see if it's classified
as a positive or a negative sentiment.
The sentence is, I absolutely loved the cinematography,
but the plot was terrible.
So we take the sentence.
We pass it through our tokenizer, which basically
breaks the sentence into smaller subwords
and maps them to some IDs that are readable by our model
that we have already loaded.
And then at the output of this model,
we get the probabilities of it being a positive
or a negative sentiment.
As we can see, the model is pretty confident,
and we're going to see where it is exactly confident.
But for now, we are going to visualize these attention
maps that basically shows what?
They show for each anchor word, which
corresponds to the rows here, which of the other words,
are the most important.
For example, let's take this word here, was.
This word, if we take it horizontally,
has the highest attention weight in the word but.
So it looks like the model cares a lot.
It looks like the word was, its representation is affected
inside the model a lot by the word
but, which makes sense because but is what introduces
the change in the tone.
The first part is more positive and the second is more negative.
And in general, all the words of the second sentence
seem to attend to the word but a lot.
For the first part of the sentence, most of the words
seem to attend to the word love.
So cinematography, it looks like the most important again
is the word love, which makes sense because what did we love?
We loved the cinematography.
So that's how we can read the heatmap.
The higher the value, the higher the weight
the anchor word the row gives to a certain other word.
The last column is very bright because--
and this is the separator token.
This is not as intuitive and not good
for our educational purposes.
But this is how attention works inside the model.
We can still do visualize the left part of the table
and try to get an idea of which parts, which combinations,
which pairs of words seemed to be kind of connected.
Was, for example, was connected to but.
As we said, terrible, also connected to but, et cetera.
And also, we can visualize this in different layers
in different parts of the network.
Here, we visualized a heat map that's around--
it's internal.
It's around the middle layer.
And finally, for lime, we already
explained how lime works for images.
For text, we are more or less trying
to answer the same question, which
is which words change the prediction if we
remove or change them.
So we create many perturbed version of the sentence
like previously we created many perturbed version of the image.
So words are randomly removed or masked.
And then we run the model on these modified sentences,
and we check how the prediction probability changes.
Afterwards, we fit a simple surrogate model
like linear regression.
The input is which words were kept or removed
as in the images which parts of the image were kept and removed.
And the output, what we're trying to learn,
is how the prediction changed when these words were removed.
And the coefficients, for example
of this linear regression model tell us
which words push the prediction positive or negative.
And then we're going to display this.
So basically, we are going to say
that positive words are shown in orange
and negative words are shown in blue.
By positive words, we mean that these words seem
to be the ones pushing towards a positive classification
and negative were the ones pushing
towards a negative classification.
So we initialize our explainer.
The class names are negative on the left and positive
on the right, which, as we remember,
the first number was extremely high.
So the model predicted that this is
negative with high confidence.
We don't care about how good the prediction is right now.
We just want to see how each word influenced the prediction
probability, basically.
So what does this plot show us?
Terrible and but were the words that
had the biggest negative contribution,
and the words loved and absolutely
were the words with the highest positive contribution, which
makes sense.
So I know it's a bit confusing with the negative and positive
parts, but if we think about it, what does this mean?
It means that when we removed the terrible word probably,
we got a much more positive signal, which
means that the terrible word, when it existed in the sentence,
was driving the prediction towards the negative part
more strongly.
That's why we draw the conclusion
that terrible was one of the words that contributed
to the negative prediction.
And here, you can see again the full sentence
with the highlighted words in terms of how positive
and how negative.
So a darker color means this word was the most important
in terms of the negative, and this--
loved was the word that was most important compared to--
towards positive, which makes sense.
OK, so this is all for today's recitation.
Some key takeaways-- different data types
need different interpretability tools.
So for tabular data, we took a look
at coefficients of the logistic regression model.
We took a look at decision trees,
which are highly interpretable.
But we didn't-- yeah, for decision trees that are
interpretable and also random forests and XGBoost models that
are not that interpretable, but we took a look at the feature
importances and the sub values.
Images-- for images, we explored the saliency maps, lime scores,
and Grad-CAM.
And for text, we explored attention maps and lime scores.
Linear and tree models are easy to interpret--
logistic regression through the coefficients, decision
trees, human readable rules.
And then samples, they have better accuracy,
but we need sub values for full explanations.
Sub provides reads global and local insights as we discussed.
Image methods provide different levels of detail.
Saliency maps give us the pixel sensitivity.
Lime gives us important regions, and Grad-CAM through
the importance--
grad-cam, through exploring the gradients
and the last convolutional layers,
it emphasizes where the model actually looks.
The language explanations show relationships
between words, word to word interactions,
and, through the lime scores, influence of each word
on the final prediction.
And yeah, as a general conclusion,
we should say that interpretability
is essential for debugging reasons, for us understanding
how the models work, and most importantly, for trust
and transparency when they are employed by practitioners.
And this is actually a big step towards transparent and fair AI.
Thank you for watching, and good luck
with the rest of the module.