INSTRUCTOR: Following the previous examples,
the key question is, which technologies can we
use to effectively represent data and knowledge on the web
to facilitate a shared understanding of meaning
among all users, including AI services?
The original idea here is the semantic web introduced in 2001
by Tim Berners-Lee, James Hendler, and Ora Lassila.
Semantic information from the web
can drive AI agents to develop services
that facilitate human life.
Services connected to the web can automatically
control local devices.
For example, they can control the volume of the entertainment
system when the phone rings or set up appointment times
by checking people's agendas.
Moreover, agents can use web knowledge
to interact with each other, providing
services that help humans.
For instance, a user AI agent can retrieve information
about prescribed treatments from a doctor's AI Agent,
looking up relevant providers close to the user's location
and well rated by trusted rating services.
All that, automatically.
To achieve this objective, the W3C, the Web Consortium,
introduced a suite of technologies
to support the so-called web of data.
The idea is to see the whole web as one database,
like a brain for the humankind.
The aim of the web of data is to empower computers
to perform valuable tasks and foster
the development of systems that facilitate
trustworthy interactions across the web.
With the semantic web efforts, W3C
envisioned a network of linked data.
Semantic web technologies empower individuals
to publish data on the web, construct vocabularies,
and formulate rules for managing and publishing data
and terminologies.
To fulfill this vision, W3C developed
standards and technologies for data representation,
vocabulary building, data querying,
and application development.
For instance, in sectors such as--
for instance, in sectors such as healthcare, life sciences,
and government, integrating decision making capabilities
into clinical research using semantic web technologies
can connect diverse forms of biological and medical
information across different institutions.
Almost a decade later, following extensive research in the field,
Google introduced groundbreaking ideas
that revolutionized how its web search engine represents
and accesses data.
The fundamental technology of these innovations
is known as knowledge graphs.
It describes a novel approach where information in the web
is no longer represented as simple strings but as things.
This departure from merely matching keywords to queries
was a significant shift.
Knowledge graphs allow users to search for people, places,
cities, sports teams, buildings, movies, and more,
instantly retrieving relevant information.
This was a crucial step in building the next generation
of search engines and other web services,
forming the foundation of the web's collective intelligence
similar to human understanding.
For instance, consider a query like Taj Mahal
in previous search engine versions.
Taj Mahal might have been treated as a keyword--
actually, two words.
So search engines look for Taj Mahal
appearing in a web document.
However, Taj Mahal can refer to the monument, the musician,
the Casino in Atlantic City, or a restaurant.
This ambiguity is the main problem of keyword-based search
engines.
Using knowledge graphs, the search engine
can predict the entity most relevant to the user query,
significantly advancing web level operations.
The key concept behind this innovation
was labeled as things, not strings.
Today, knowledge graphs incorporate
all web of data technologies in an effort
to harness diverse, dynamic, and large-scale data collections.
The primary objective of knowledge graphs
is to organize and connect data, facilitating a deeper
understanding and analysis of the information published
on the web.
Data provide information about entities,
so formally naming entities and providing reference to them
is very important.
Here is the Wikipedia description of the film La La
Land.
It provides helpful information in English
accessible to English-speaking readers.
In this text we find various entities, such as individuals,
movies, or cities.
Examples include Emma Stone, Whiplash, and Los Angeles.
Some of these entities are widely recognized
while others may be lesser known.
If we examine closely, we'll notice
that many of these entities have hyperlinks
connected to their names or relevant text strings
with other web pages or sources of information.
For example, there are hyperlinks
that lead to other Wikipedia articles, IMDb
pages, or GeoNames entries.
Although these hyperlinks may look different,
they share a similar technical structure or format.
These lengthy strings serve as references to resources,
defining the specific entities and providing information
about them.
They are more informative than the name
of the entity in English.
Actually, this is a universal approach of identifying things
through the web compared to the more restricted,
natural language names in one of the many natural languages
of the world.
Every entity of the world has a web name.
It is considered as the web resource.
These names are represented by the Uniform Resource
Identifiers, the URIs.
A URI is a unique sequence of characters
that formally identifies a logical or physical resource.
URIs can be employed to identify a wide range of entities,
including real-world objects, like people and places,
abstract concepts, or informational resources
such as web pages and books.
Examples of URIs include URLs, email addresses, book ISBNs,
telephone numbers, et cetera.
While some URIs provide access to resources
via the internet, e.g, by clicking the hyperlink,
others do not.
The most common approach to formally describing things
is by categorizing them into relevant classes.
In the Wikipedia article of our example,
we can see several references to classes
ranging from general categories such as city script or film,
to more specific ones like romantic musical film or jazz
pianist.
Similarly to the entities, some of the classes have their URIs.
Examples of URIs are hyperlinks to other Wikipedia resources
that provide more detailed descriptions of the class.
See, for example, the romantic musical film.
Given that romantic musical film is a movie genre,
and movie genres play a crucial role in movie recommendation
systems, one would expect to find a comprehensive movie
genre terminology somewhere on the web.
Indeed, detailed movie genre classifications
can be found in IMDb, Wikipedia, and other sources.
These classifications often provide
names of classes, that is, the terminology of the domain,
as well as the information about how specific classes relate
to each other, for example, as subclasses
of more general classes.
This is a first example of terminological knowledge
representation that may be used by automated reasoning.
For example, the subclass relation
of love story and romantic film lead to the conclusion
that every romantic film is a love story.
These formal representations of classifications
are referred to by various terms,
including terminologies, hierarchies, taxonomies,
and ontologies.
They all serve to organize and categorize
information in structured ways or as we formally
say, to provide specifications of conceptualizations.
Until now, we described how we formally
assign names to entities and classes using URIs.
The next step is to link entity names to class names,
connecting entity URIs to class URIs.
This is the formal representation
of categorizations.
Moreover, we generalize that to describe not only relationships
between entities to classes but also between entities
to entities or classes to classes.
In this description of La La Land,
there are many natural language references to relationships.
For instance, the is-a relationship
signifies categorization La La Land is a romantic musical film.
Other relationships relate films to directors,
awards to actors, individuals to universities,
filming locations to places, and so on.
Examples are written by, directed by, appear in,
et cetera.
All relationships have their own names and descriptions
on the web as web resources using, again, URIs.
The link is to a web resource that formally
defines the relationship.
Semantic references to entities, classes, and relationships
using URIs function similarly to words in natural language.
However, in this case, the meaning of the reference
is explicitly defined rather than relying
on human interpretation.
When we use words in natural language,
their meaning exists in our minds
if we understand the language.
We share this meaning as long as we speak the same language.
With web resources, the meaning is explicitly defined.
It is embedded in the URI, which may be more complex but far
less ambiguous than words.
Just as words are combined to form meaningful sentences,
we will now explore how URIs are structured to formally define
conceptualizations.
For example, we can formally represent information
such as La La Land is a romantic musical film by simply putting
together three URIs by just writing a triple of their URIs.
Bringing everything together, the only missing piece
is a way to represent triples of URIs.
A natural way to model them is as a graph, where
nodes represent entities or classes,
and edges represent the relationships.
This is formally represented using the resource description
framework, RDF, the W3C standard web language
for describing and exchanging data and knowledge.
RDF offers a universal language, or more precisely,
a standard model for data and knowledge exchange
across the web.
Despite their simplicity, RDF descriptions
are highly expressive, providing elegant and intuitive methods
for formally exchanging conceptual specifications
on the web.
In this manner, the majority of human understandable
descriptions found in Wikipedia can be represented in a graph
form using RDF syntax.
For instance, the information provided by the sentence,
La La Land is a romantic musical film directed
by Damien Chazelle, can be represented
by a graph containing two triples.
Using RDF, we can formally represent declarations,
as we do with natural language descriptions.
Of course, we cannot represent all information of the text
in the simple triple form.
The reason is that human language expressivity far
exceeds that of any formal knowledge representation
language in AI.
On the other hand, when exchanging conceptualization,
thoughts, and knowledge, greater expressivity often introduces
ambiguity, and ambiguity brings complexity, confusion,
and misconceptions.
Humans have the ability to handle misconceptions,
whereas machines, at least for now, do not.
So when designing a language to share knowledge with machines,
symbol is beautiful.
The key question now is whether even the limited expressivity
of triples can still be used to represent
more complex knowledge, not just classification or relationships
between entities but also the axiomatic knowledge of domain.
For instance, it would be valuable to encode
knowledge such as anyone who has directed a film is a director.
A film cannot be both a thriller and a family movie.
Any film that has won a major award
is widely recognized by the general public.
To address this, W3C has developed an additional language
that builds on RDF, enhancing its expressive capabilities
for representing various forms of axiomatic knowledge.
It is the web ontology language, OWL.
It is important to highlight that all OWLs expressive
capabilities are grounded in formal semantics,
ensuring the elimination of ambiguity.
Additionally, OWL is supported by automated reasoning tools,
which leverage its axioms to infer new knowledge.
Knowledge created using OWL can be published on the web
and become shared knowledge accessible to those developing
AI services.
This structured knowledge is commonly
referred to as ontology.
Examples include general ontologies
such as DBpedia, which transforms Wikipedia
descriptions into a structured, standardized format, SNOMED,
which captures and organizes complex medical knowledge,
et cetera.