INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's recitation regarding
interpreting machine learning models
across different modalities.
So today, we're going to focus on concepts
that you came across the explainability lecture
of this module.
And we want to emphasize how important an explainable AI is
for transparency, fairness, et cetera.
Machine learning models that are used in practice
should be as interpretable as possible.
And this is, first and foremost, because we
are more confident about what the model learns
and how it behaves.
And also, it increases the chances
of higher adherence of people--
of practitioners, basically, to AI machine learning models,
in general.
So we're going to explore interpretability
across tabular data, images, and language data.
We're going to first start with tabular data.
We're going to work with these adult income data set.
And we're going to see how we can retrieve interpretability
when we use different machine learning models
that you have probably already seen in other modules.
So today, we are not going to explain how these models work.
We are just going to only focus on the interpretability aspect
of these models.
Next, we're going to move on to image interpretability, where
we're going to see some cool ways of visualizing which parts
of the images contribute more to the final predictions of images
models.
And then, last but not least, we are
going to go over a language example,
and we are going to see how attention maps help understand
which word has-- which words are important for each anchor word.
And we're going to also explore LIME,
which is another method that is widely used for explainability.
So the goal, again, is not to dive into how the models work
or what's the difference between the tabular, the image
models, the language models.
We just want to explore ways of using interpretability.
So let's start with the first modality, the tabular data.
We are going to use the Adult Census Income Data Set, which is
a publicly available data set.
And we are talking about a classification problem here.
So we are going to train models that aim to predict whether
a certain person earns more than $50k per year.
It's a binary classification problem.
We have the label 0 if its sample--
its person has an income of less than $50k.
And we have the target 1 for the people that have an income above
$50k.
We are going to explore a logistic regression
model, a decision tree, random forest, XGBoost.
And we're going to use the SHAP explainer inside the--
we're going to use the SHAP explainer on the XGBoost
to get some idea about explainability.
We are going to simplify the features a bit
because this data set has a lot of categorical features.
And we think it's more intuitive to just preprocess them and keep
the most informative and easy-to-parse features.
First of all, as always, we load our data set
and the different dependencies, different packages that
are required for the notebook.
We are also going to load the Adult Data Set.
It is available online.
These here are the names of the different features.
Income is the final column, the target column.
And the rest are just our X's, our input features.
We are removing rows with null values.
The Adult Data Set is pretty big,
so we have the luxury to do that.
And then we are also going to only change
the features to keep only this.
We are keeping the age, the sex, the education number,
hours per week, capital gain, capital loss,
and marital status.
And we're going to explain what each of these features
corresponds to.
But the idea is that we want to use a simplified
subset of the features.
We are encoding the income column as a binary column
because as we said, we want to solve a binary classification
problem.
So if the income is above $50k, then we are encoding this as 1.
This is a Boolean evaluation.
And also, we are simplifying the sex feature.
We are also simplifying the married feature.
So if someone is married, regardless
of other more specific information about the marriage,
we encode it as 1.
If they are unmarried, encoded it as 0.
This is how our data set looks like.
We have the features that we mentioned before.
And now let's understand what each of these features mean.
So first, the age, the sex and the marital status
correspond to demographic and personal attributes.
So age is, of course, the age of the individual in years.
Sex is encoded as 1 for males and 0 for females.
And marital status is encoded as 1 for married and 0
for unmarried.
Then we have the education and skill indicators, which
is basically the education num.
This is a numeric score representing highest education
level.
So the highest the value of this feature,
the more educated the person is.
And then we also have work and financial attributes,
which are the hours per week, which
is the average number of hours worked per week;
capital gains, which are investment gains-- for example,
stocks, real estate.
For most people, this is 0, but it's still
an informative factor.
And capital loss is investment losses used for tax purposes.
The target variable, as we said earlier, is the income.
And we have binarized it in a way that we assign 1
if the income is larger than $50k and 0 otherwise.
Now, we define our X's and our Y's.
The Y's the target variable, the income.
We split into train and test set to avoid data leakage.
And we have our numerical and our categorical columns.
And we define these preprocessing pipeline here
that basically says that, for numerical values,
use a standard scaler to scale our features.
And for categorical, which are binary in our case,
we don't need to do anything.