INSTRUCTOR: So let's start with the first section
of today's recitation, which is simple prompt engineering.
So prompt engineering is a concept
that became very popular after ChatGPT emerged.
And it basically refers to the way
of writing your prompts to large language models
in order to get the output that you want
or that best suits your needs.
I assume that everyone or most of you in their everyday lives
use ChatGPT for various tasks depending on your job
or even for everyday life reasons.
And you might have also observed that ChatGPT
doesn't require very thoughtful or well-structured prompts.
We can more or less write sentences
with wrong grammar, wrong syntax, or very vague prompts.
And most of the times, ChatGPT or other LLMs,
like Gemini from Google or DeepSeek
can definitely understand what we want them to do,
and they do it successfully.
But there is a very important point
that needs to be made here.
ChatGPT and all the other models I just
mentioned, although, we feel like they just
work without needing carefully designed prompts,
this happens only because they are massive.
These models are huge.
They have a lot of billions of parameters.
And in order for them to run, they
require extremely expensive GPUs and lots of memory.
For that reason, it is impossible to load these models
and use them programmatically for coding or other machine
learning tasks in an environment like Google Colab, for example.
And even if someone was able to load them
in a huge GPU they might have, it
would also be very slow for them to work.
That is why it is still relevant to focus on large language
models that are smaller, their number of parameters
is smaller compared to ChatGPT.
So for example-- that's why today we
want to focus on models that we can load on Google Colab
and that they can run fast on it.
So we selected two models for these recitations
demonstrations, Llama and OpenChat.
Llama, as you might have guessed from my previous reference
to it, is a model developed by Meta.
There are multiple versions of the Llama model,
but today, we are going to focus on the 8 billion
parameter model, which is one of the small models that Meta has.
OpenChat is another LLM that also has
around 7 billion parameters.
Both of these models are definitely
less strong than ChatGPT 4 that is currently
available in the ChatGPT website.
In order to have a clearer picture of how
the models compare to each other,
we are going to use the exact same prompt to see what outputs
we get from the Llama model, the OpenChat model, and ChatGPT,
the ChatGPT 4 version.
And we're going to see how much better ChatGPT is.
But we should always take into consideration
the fact that the models that run behind it
are much, much, much bigger.
First of all, let's load the Llama and OpenChat models.
We are going to use the Hugging Face Transformers Library.
And we are going to also use 4-bit quantization in order
to save GPU memory.
Here, we first specify--
we first import some of the packages that we want,
and then we specify the model IDs for Llama and OpenChat.
These are the paths as one can find them in Hugging Face.
And then for each of the two models, we load the tokenizer.
We specify the quantization configuration, which is,
as I mentioned, 4-bit, and then we also load the pretrained
version of the model of each of the models, and basically,
we load their weights.
As you can see here, the models are loaded, both Llama
and OpenChat.
And then, after we load the models,
we have to write a generate response function that we'll
take as an input, a text prompt, and we'll
use one of the language models that we want to produce
a natural language response.
What this function does is that here it first tokenizes
the prompt, and it makes sure that the input is
at the same device as the model, in our case, at GPU.
And then, we are going to use the generate function
where we specify the input.
We set the maximum number of tokens
that we want the model to generate,
and we also want to allow some randomness in the output.
This is achieved through these parameters
here, which correspond to some kind of sampling.
And the goal of this is to make the responses more varied.
The default length of the responses we have set here
is 256, as you can see in the argument here.
And basically, we use a tokenizer
to decode the output of the model generation
and get a human-like reply.
We also specify this run all models function.
What this does is that it iterates
over the different models, which in our case
are these two, Llama and OpenChat.
And it generates responses for the specific prompt
that we have provided.
Now, we are going to explore different kinds of prompts
and the reasons for which one could potentially
want to use them.
The first and simplest type of prompt,
which is also the type of prompt that we usually give to ChatGPT,
and then if ChatGPT doesn't give us the answer we want,
we might move to more sophisticated prompts,
is called zero-shot learning.
So zero-shot learning basically refers to a type of prompt
where the model is asked to perform a task by just relying
on the general knowledge it has been trained on
and the prompt itself.
So it doesn't receive any kind of example
that could potentially guide it into what we want it to do.
Of course, as you might imagine--
and this is more evident when we work with smaller models.
This might lead to hallucination,
which is the case where the model kind of makes up facts
confidently without them being grounded.
It can lead to potential bias or a lower accuracy.
An example of a zero-shot prompt is this one here.
I love La La Land.
I hate Babylon.
Sentiment and question mark.
What this means is that we are asking our model
to give us the type of sentiment that these two sentences imply.
Let's see what each of the two models
actually gave as an output.
For Llama, after it outputs the prompt,
it starts talking about how they are
big fans of Damien Chazelle, who is the director of La La Land.
And it kind of imitates a person that
would use these two sentences.
So it does not ever--
if you read the whole, whole output,
it does not ever give us a specific characterization
of the sentiment of these two sentences.
What this means is that the model did not
understand the task.
Similarly, for OpenChat, it starts elaborating, again,
imitating a user that would potentially
say these two sentences.
It starts talking about how they have a complicated relationship
with movies about Hollywood.
And it kind of justifies these two sentences,
and it never gives us the exact sentiment that we want.
One thing that you will observe in all
of the outputs we are going to explore today
is that some of the sentences might be cut abruptly.
This is because we have set this maximum number of tokens
that can be generated to 256.
So if the model wants to keep producing an output
and it reaches the 256 limit, it will just abruptly cut
the generated output.
So conclusion is that none of the two small models
were able to understand what we wanted them to do.
Let's see what-- and this is a screenshot from ChatGPT.
Let's see what happened when we used the same prompt on ChatGPT
4.
ChatGPT immediately realized what we wanted to do.
It gave us this output where basically says "I love La La
Land" corresponds to a positive sentiment, and "I hate Babylon"
corresponds to a negative sentiment.
So the overall sentiment is mixed or neutral.
And it also doesn't have the problem
of having to cut a sentence in half or these things
that one has to deal with when they work with smaller LLMs.
How can zero-shot learning, which
is the most naive way of approaching, of talking in a way
to an LLM, be improved?
The extension of zero-shot learning is few-shot learning.
So few-shot learning is basically
when a model is given a small number of examples of a task
within the prompt itself to help it understand the expected input
and output format before answering a new query.
So the idea is that here we give an example of "I
love La La Land.
Sentiment is positive."
That is what the answer of the model should be.
"I hate Babylon.
Sentiment is negative."
And then, we provide a new sentence
for which we want the model to actually produce
the corresponding sentiment.
The sentence is "Oppenheimer was very interesting."
And we are asking the model to fill the sentiment prompt.
Let's see what happened with Llama.
So Llama decided that "Oppenheimer was very
interesting" is a neutral sentiment, which is valid.
One could be more inclined to say that it is positive,
but it's also not super enthusiastic, so
neutral is acceptable.
At least now, Llama understood what it was supposed to do.
However, as you can see, it also started
producing so many other examples of sentences that
contain some kind of sentiment.
And it produces outputs without us asking them to do that.
OpenChat also did the same thing.
It classified the sentiment of Oppenheimer as positive.
At least now, although both models
start outputting some random stuff at the end, at least
now they understood what we wanted them to do.
Let's see what ChatGPT did.
As you might imagine, it just outputs a single sentence
that is--
that "Oppenheimer was very interesting"
carries a positive sentiment.
Another type of prompt is called Chain of Thought.
Chain-of-Thought prompting is a technique
that people use when they want to encourage a language
model to reason step by step before giving a final answer.
So instead of jumping straight to the conclusion,
the model gets instructions about what steps to follow.
And these, for at least complex or multi-step tasks,
has been shown to improve accuracy.
Here we are going to go over a simple example
of a Chain of Thought that is a combination of math and physics.
Here, we have the sentence, "A train travel kilometers in one
hour and 30 minutes," and we basically want the LLM
to compute the speed of the train in kilometers per hour.
Instead of just saying calculate the speed in kilometers
per hour, the Chain of Thought suggests
that we specify the specific steps before we
reach the final computation.
So the first step that we instruct the model to do
is to convert the time to hours.
The second step is to use the speed formula.
And we also provide the formula.
And the third step is to compute the speed.
So Llama actually followed the steps.
And as you can see here, so convert the time to hours,
one hour and 30 minutes is 1.5 hours.
The speed formula, so it's 60 kilometers divided by 1.5 hours,
and then the third step, the speed is 40km/h.
As far as OpenChat is concerned, you will see here that before
performing the three steps, it gives this answer of 80km/h
without any reason.
This is an example where small language models or smaller
than ChatGPT can also provide wrong answers.
And we're going to see how we will avoid it
later on by just changing the prompt a bit.
Eventually, in the rest of the chunks of text
that OpenChat gave as an output, we
can see that the response is correct.
It calculated 40km/h, but it is definitely confusing to see
an output like this.
When we asked ChatGPT to do the exact same thing, of course,
it followed the three steps, and it gave us the right output
of 40km/h.
Apart from the fact that we selected Chain of Thought
as a type of prompting to solve this task,
the exact prompt also matters.
So to address this 80km/h random output from open chat if we just
write the Chain-of-Thought prompt in a simpler,
in a less explicit way, so basically,
if we write a train travels 60 kilometers in one hour and 30
minutes, what is its average speed in kilometers per hour?
And we just say, let's think step by step,
we can see that OpenChat applies the steps itself without us
outlining them in the way that we did earlier,
and it actually gives the right response immediately.
This is just to show you that the same model
can give different outputs when they
are asked to do the same task with slightly different prompts,
even in the same type of prompting,
but with different phrasing.
Another type of prompt is role instruction.
Role instruction is basically when
we tell the model who it should act as,
and this can affect the tone, the style, and the reasoning.
It basically asks the model to imitate a certain, for example,
person or a certain situation and respond accordingly.
Here in our example, we want our model
to imitate a senior oncologist, and we
want the model to explain in simple terms what chemotherapy
is to a worried patient.
Both Llama and OpenChat are effective in doing that here.
And it's actually interesting that Llama, in order
to give us an output that is even more realistic,
generated a synthetic fake example of a patient's case,
and then it gave an example of how a senior oncologist would
respond in this specific case.
OpenChat gave a more general description
about how chemotherapy is, and it actually
structured it in a way that can be provided to a patient.
For example, it used these sentences.
Remember, the purpose of chemotherapy
is to help you get better, and things like that.
Of course, ChatGPT, when we asked it,
also performed this task very, very successfully.
This is something to be expected.
And then, we can move on to the next type of prompt,
which is style prompt or style instruction.
This refers to when we tell the model how
to communicate in terms of tone, formality,
regardless of the content of what we ask or the role.
So here, for example, we have asked our models
to write a short poem in Shakespeare style
about artificial intelligence.
And of course, these poems are different.
You can take a look, and you will find them, I suppose,
quite interesting and funny.
They're actually pretty good.
Both of the models are capable of doing that very successfully.
And one might ask, why one would want to do that?
It's when you want to generate something
from scratch that imitates things that are already
out there and the models have-- these specific models
have been trained on.
The next type of prompt we're going to see today
is prompt chaining.
Prompt chaining is basically a technique
where we have a complex task, and we break it
into smaller steps using the output of one
prompt as the input for the next.
This is something that can be very useful for people
that use ChatGPT as well.
So instead of giving ChatGPT a full paragraph
of all the sequential things that we
want it to do, we can break these things in smaller prompts
and first ask it, for example, to summarize the text we have,
then as a second prompt, after the summarization,
after the summary is ready, we can ask it to, let's say,
extract keywords, et cetera.
These can be more effective than just providing
a single big prompt that asks the model
to do everything at once.
Here, this is an example of prompt chaining in a medical QA
setting.
So we asked the model to first extract
the key symptoms from a very simple medical note, which
is the patient presents with cough, fever, and difficulty
breathing, then we ask the model to use
the extracted symptoms to suggest possible conditions that
are relevant.
And then as a third step, we ask the model to take the conditions
that it suggested, and based on those,
recommend different diagnostic tests.
And also, we ask the model to provide the full reasoning.
So here as you can see, for example, in the Llama output,
the key symptoms are, of course, cough, fever, and difficulty
breathing.
This was the first step.
Then based on the symptoms, the possible conditions
are, for example, pneumonia, bronchitis, asthma, et cetera.
And there is also an explanation of why each of these conditions
should be considered.
And then based on the symptoms and possible conditions,
so based on the outputs of the last two--
of the first two small prompts, we
can see here that Llama recommends these two
examinations, these two tests-- chest X-ray and blood count.
OpenChat follows a same approach,
where it first outlines the symptoms,
then it lists the conditions, and then
it also lists a set of diagnostic tests.
It is also interesting to see that there
are differences in the tests that are suggested.
For example, OpenChat also suggest a COVID test
and a pulse oximetry test.
This way of prompting can actually be very, very helpful
in different contexts.