INSTRUCTOR: So now, let's consider a principal method
we used in the past for classification,
namely logistic regression.
Recall that y equals plus 1, as we have discussed,
means that passing the bar exam.
And y equals minus 1 is failing the bar exam.
So we seek to predict the probability of a success outcome
for the dependent variable y, passing the exam,
as a function of independent variables x1, x2, xk.
Recall that the likelihood of y equals
plus 1 is given by the formula in the slide, which
is the classical logistic regression formula.
So how do we select the beta coefficients,
the coefficients that multiply the variables to make
the prediction?
We optimize over the beta variables
the likelihood of achieving that.
But in addition, now, to optimizing over beta,
over the parameters, we can also optimize--
you can select which variables to flip.
So that we flip the variables, as well as
changing the betas together to optimize the likelihood further.
So this can be modeled.
This mathematical model can be modeled as a nonlinear,
in this case, binary optimization
problem of the types we have discussed
in the foundational module on AI prescriptive.
And this is given here.
The details are not so important.
The key here is it can be done easily.
So in the end of the day, by solving an optimization problem,
we find the parameters of the logistic regression.
And at the same time, we find which variables
to flip in such a way that we achieve a parity,
namely that the difference of ratios
between those white students-- the percentage of white students
who pass the exam minus the percentage of Black students
that pass the exam is less than epsilon for an epsilon
being a pre-specified characteristic, which is we
utilize it to be 1%.
So let us apply this methodology to the data set that I mentioned
about passing the bar exam.
This data set originates from this study in the late '90s that
examined whether the bar exam taken by the law students
in the United States is biased against ethnic minorities.
It contains anonymized historical information,
including age, LSAT scores, first year law school
GPA, cumulative law GPA, the GPA in the law school,
as well as the undergraduate GPA.
So it has achievement.
It had, of course, age, and then achievement
of scores for a variety of characteristics.
So now, the graph here shows the differences
between Blacks and whites on various characteristics
involving the LSAT, the GPA in the law school,
the undergraduate GPA, and so forth.
And you see that white students, the ones in blue,
have overall, on the left, stronger scores
than their Black counterparts.
Whereas on the right graph, this is the same thing regarding
gender, we see that male students, at least in two
of the three categories, are slightly above the averages
relative to female students, on the other hand,
on the law school GPA, the female students are stronger.
In other words, these data sets are biased with alpha on race
is 0.3.
And the alpha, the bias on gender, is much lower, 0.02.
So in other words, there is very little bias on gender.
But there is quite a lot of bias for race.
So the story is similar regarding
LSAT scores, the undergraduate GPA, and so forth.
So this is the situation we aim to remedy.
So we apply for these data sets that exhibit some bias regarding
race anyway at the level of 0.3 to bring it
to basically very little bias, epsilon equals 1%, 0.001.
And what we observe, if you focus
on the vertical that says LR for Logistic Regression,
so regarding the white applications,
you observe that in the data, this is the so-called z-score.
I remind you that z-score of z-score
of a person minus the mean divided
by the standard deviation.
And we observe that for the white population, if you apply
this optimization method, we don't materially
change the scores before what is in the data
and what is after the optimization.
However, with the Black population
there is a slight decrease.
We make it less meritocratic, so to speak, but very little,
slight.
So I repeat again that the z-scores of the attributes,
the GPA, the LSAT scores for admitted students
among the white population do not change significantly
even after employing the mixed integer optimization approach.
However, the z-scores of attributes for admitted students
among the Black subpopulation decreases slightly,
signifying that lowering the threshold for passing the bar
exam for Black students, but in such a way
that we help to achieve demographic parity.
So we very much achieve the getting demographic parity,
namely the percentages of whites who
pass minus the percentage of Blacks who pass
is basically now within 1%, where
it used to be 30% apart at a very small price on meritocracy.
So now, of course, this is a machine
learning quantitative method.
What we would like now to do is we would like to understand
in an actionable way, using machine learning again,
what are the characteristics of these students
for which the outcome labels are flipped after employing
the mixed integer optimization approach?
So what we do on that, we construct
a new data set based on the results of the optimization
approach.
Each observation is labeled as one of the following-- positive,
this is where the label flipped to a positive label,
negative, this is where the outcome changed
to a negative label, or no change.
So now we have, because the mixed integer optimization
approach could actually change the label to positive,
or change the label to negative, or no change,
so now this is a three class classification problem.
So we have the attributes, the xi's.
This is the age, the undergraduate GPA, LSAT,
and so forth.
And then the outcome is whether the outcome changed,
it flipped in the positive way, or in a negative way,
or no change.
And then we apply in an optimal classification tree,
the methodology we used in the foundational module
on machine learning.
And what we observe is this tree that
makes partitions of this data set
and then outputs when you make a change or not.
In that way, we have now an interpretable way of deciding
when we flip or we don't flip.
Now this particular model, this tree
has an area under the curve of 0.67, not spectacular.
But on the other hand, insightful
in telling us what are the key characteristics of the variables
that result in flipping.
So, for example, let us summarize the understanding.
The logistic regression model identifies the following
criteria, based on GPA and LSAT scores
to select the most meritocratic students
among the Black subpopulation.
So if the LSAT is above 34.75 and the z-score of the GPA
is less than minus 0.86, so these are stronger scores,
or the LSAT is less than 34.75 and the undergraduate GPA
is above 215, those Black students who
were assigned to a negative label,
we flipped them to a positive label.
So notice that they have either a higher LSAT score or higher
undergraduate GPA.
The model also identifies criteria
for the least meritorious students
among the white population.
So in this case, there are two categories.
This is now among the white population,
the LSAT is bigger than 3475 and the cumulative GPA z-score
is less than minus 156.
Or the LSAT is less than 3475 and the cumulative z-score
of the GPA is less than minus 1.08.
So those white students who were assigned a positive label,
we now flip them to a negative label.
So in other words, it identifies the most meritorious Black
students, we flip.
And then the least meritorious white students,
we flip from positive to negative.
You can go into further analysis.
These numbers discuss in more detail about the various nodes
that make no change.
For example, among the Black population,
if the LSAT is already greater than 3475
and the GPA is bigger than minus 0.86, which
is 93.4% of the students who actually pass the bar exam,
these are Black students that already have passed the exam,
they are very qualified, we do not change.
And similarly, we have Black students who are not
qualified enough using the criteria that you observe,
we don't change.
In other words, we only change the Black students
that are close to the border.
And we pass the exam.
And on the white population, similarly,
those students that are most qualified, we'd make no change.
Or white students that are not qualified enough, also,
we make no change.
In other words, we holistically look at these variables.
And we only flip those on the boundary, as I have indicated.