INSTRUCTOR: Next, we will explore a key service that
automates communication processes
with AI models in multiple component AI systems--
reasoning.
Reasoning is the process of deriving conclusions
from facts and knowledge, transforming implicit knowledge
into explicit.
Through reasoning services, we can standardize AI processes
while ensuring guarantees for consistency, correctness,
and accuracy of AI models.
Additionally, with reasoning, we can enable explainability,
allowing for better interpretation
of AI-generated results.
We can also enhance prompt engineering or search
and retrieval by providing contextual understanding
and domain knowledge analysis capabilities.
There are various types of reasoning.
The three main types are deductive, inductive,
and abductive reasoning.
Deductive reasoning allows us to derive conclusions from facts
by applying logical rules.
For instance, we know that all patients
with bacterial pneumonia have elevated white blood cell
counts.
We also know that John has bacterial pneumonia.
So as a conclusion, John's white blood cell count
should be elevated.
Inductive reasoning helps us identify relationships
between facts, allowing us to derive general rules
from specific observations.
For example, we observe that 90% of pneumonia patients
in hospital had a fever.
We conclude that pneumonia patients likely develop a fever.
Abductive reasoning helps us identify possible causes
that explain observed events.
For instance, we observe that a patient
has lung capacity and fever.
As possible explanations, we conclude
that the patient has pneumonia, the most likely,
or lung cancer, less likely, or pulmonary edema,
possible but unlikely.
Most reasoning services used in multicomponent AI systems
are categorized on these fundamental types.
For example, determining the context
for extracting relevant data, such as inferring
the possible intent behind the user's query to an AI system,
is a problem of abductive reasoning.
The traditional approach to AI reasoning relies on symbolic AI.
In previous lectures, we described systematic approaches
to automated reasoning, focusing on deductive reasoning
through knowledge expansion algorithms.
Modern LLMs also exhibit automated reasoning
capabilities.
Of course, they do not perform reasoning
in the same way humans do.
They generate outputs by recognizing and utilizing
statistical patterns learned from their training data.
LLM reasoning arises from the model's ability
to predict the next token in a sequence, capturing
patterns of logic, mathematics, and common sense learned
from its training data.
This creates the illusion of formal reasoning,
but there is no genuine understanding,
intentional thought process, or structured reasoning mechanism
behind LLM reasoning.
As a result, LLM's conclusions are not always correct,
even if they are inferred from valid knowledge and facts.
On the other hand, automated reasoning in symbolic AI systems
relies on sound inference rules.
If the knowledge and facts are correct,
symbolic AI engines will always produce logically
valid conclusions.
It is important to deeply understand this distinction
to choose between LLM reasoning and symbolic reasoning
in practical applications.
Before exploring how reasoning is performed by symbolic AI
systems and LLMs, let's first examine
how information is represented and stored within these systems.
We revisit the example from lectures on symbolic AI using
the Wikipedia description of the movie La La Land.
The first sentence of the text is represented in LLMs
with the use of tokens.
Tokens are the fundamental unit of information representation
in language models.
Tokens are data units that represent short character
sequences.
They are not necessarily full words
but can include subwords, individual characters,
or even punctuation marks.
A general rule of thumb is that one token corresponds
to approximately four characters in common English text.
This means that 75 words typically
translate to around 100 tokens.
The GPT-4 tokenizer, which is used in ChatGPT,
identifies 20 tokens in the example sentence.
Here, we see the separation into tokens,
which leads to a dense representation of the sentence,
which is not fully aligned to the words used in the meaning.
These tokens are then encoded and are
assigned unique identifiers, the IDs,
allowing each sentence to be represented
as a vector containing the token IDs.
The operation of LLMs is based on the encoding
of tokens in another space using embeddings.
The mapping from the token space to the embedding space
is done by encoders.
For instance, the encoder used by ChatGPT maps tokens from each
text into a vector space with at least 1,500 dimensions.
This is the small embedding encoding vector
representing the tokenized text in a high-dimensional space.
This is the embedding vector representing our input text.
Embedding vectors are text representations
with strong statistical properties,
such as capturing the likelihood of words appearing
next to each other in a text.
However, they lose direct semantic reference
to the actual words, at least as humans perceive them,
meaning they no longer retain a direct, interpretable connection
to the original linguistic meaning.
Therefore, this representation is
machine understandable but not human
understandable as it is statistics intensive rather than
knowledge intensive.
On the other hand, in symbolic AI,
information is represented explicitly and structurally.
Remember, from previous lectures on symbolic AI,
the same example sentence can be represented
as a set of formal statements that explicitly
capture the intended meaning.
These statements form a structured knowledge
about the specific subject.
Specifically, we write that the description refers to the film
La La Land, which is a romantic musical film directed
and written by Damien Chazelle in 2016
and was produced in the United States.
In modern symbolic AI systems, this information
is represented on the web as a graph, where nodes represent
entities or classes, and edges represent their relationships.
Knowledge representation languages
have been standardized for graph data representation,
enabling formal semantic descriptions at the web level.
In the lecture on symbolic AI, we describe these technologies.
In the case of LLMs, we observe that embeddings
capture statistical correlations of the domain
by encoding them in valued relationships in a form that
is very effective but not human understandable.
In symbolic AI systems, domain relationships
are recorded at a semantic level, represented
as formal rules.
For example, we can record that every romantic film is a love
story.
We observe that these statements are
represented in a formal manner.
And whether they describe events or rules,
they remain human understandable while
following syntactic rules that make them machine readable.