INSTRUCTOR: Within this context, let's
explore how AI explanations should ideally
be presented to the user to ensure transparency.
We begin with an example from the medical field,
an AI-assisted diagnosis system.
During the learning phase, the AI
is trained on the data set that includes
multimodal data such as patient records in tabular format,
along with medical data like MRIs, EEGs,
and other diagnostic images.
In the inference phase, the system
assists doctors in disease diagnosis
by generating predictions for a specific patient.
Understanding the data used to train AI systems
is crucial for assessing their reliability and fairness.
Factors like data source, labeling accuracy, data set
size, and potential biases must be considered
to ensure transparency and fairness
in AI-assisted diagnosis systems.
Moreover, understanding the output
of an AI-assisted diagnosis system
is necessary for its integration into
real-world medical workflows.
The system's output, which may include predicted diagnosis
or risk assessments, usually offers insights
like a confidence score or uncertainty measures.
This could be something like 85% likelihood of a tumor.
In evaluating the AI system suitability
for using clinical practice, key considerations
include its accuracy, precision, and reliability.
So we should examine the frequency
of errors, such as false positives and negatives,
as well as when the system performs well or poorly.
To understand how the AI system makes predictions,
we need to examine the key factors influencing
its decisions.
What features does the system Consider Does it rely on patient
demographics, lab results, or imaging data?
How specific features such as age or gender impact
predictions?
How are different features weighted,
and which ones are more influential?
Finally, what kind of algorithm is used,
and how were its parameters set?
During the inference phase, it is
important to understand why the AI
system made a specific prediction
for a specific instance.
To do this, we need to examine which features
influenced its decision.
What aspects of this instance determine the outcome?
Likewise, why was this instance not classified differently?
If two instances receive the same prediction,
what shared characteristics led to that result?
If two instances receive different predictions,
what key differences led to this divergence?
Also, we need to understand how an instance can receive
a different prediction, what changes would alter
the outcome of the AI system.
What is the smallest feature adjustment
needed to shift the prediction?
How should the specific feature change
to achieve a different result?
What happens if a key feature changes?
How does it respond to a completely different instance?
Let's turn, now, our attention to the type of explanations.
The first crucial factor to understand
is the data set the AI system was trained on.
First, we need to understand the source of the data.
Is it from hospitals?
From research institutions?
From publicly available medical data sets?
From private health providers?
The source is important for assessing its credibility
and scope.
For example, a data source explanation
could inform for the type of data--
in our example, chest X-ray images--
its sources-- in our example, radiology departments
of hospitals, both open data sets and hospital databases,
all anonymized-- and potential processing of the data--
in our example, human curation.
Second, it's essential to understand
the data labeling process to assess the labeling credibility.
For example, are experts, radiologists, pathologists,
or other medical professionals involved
in the labeling process?
How many of them?
And with which labeling methodology?
Is there any other automated labeling process, for example,
associating manual annotations found in patient records
or involving automated labeling systems?
This information is crucial, as the accuracy of the ground truth
directly influences the reliability of the model.
An example of data labeling explanation could include who
labeled the image-- here, board-certified radiologists--
the diagnostic labels-- here, pneumonia, et cetera--
and how consensus is reached, particularly
in challenging cases--
here, multiple experts.
Another issue to consider is the size
of the data set, for example, the number of patient records,
MRIs, EEGs, or other medical samples used for training.
A small or imbalanced data set can lead to biased predictions,
so understanding these gaps helps us
identify potential limitations.
An example of data size explanation
could clarify, what is the size of the data set?
Here, 1.2 million medical images.
Its internal structure-- here, 500,000 CT scans, et cetera.
And how it is split in the training process
to ensure model generalization-- here, 80% for training,
10% for validation, and 10% for testing.
Of course, although it is highly undesirable,
almost every data set is biased.
So it's important to understand possible data set biases.
Biases can arise from underrepresentation
of certain patient groups, variations in equipment,
geographical limitations, or historical disparities.
For example, one data size bias explanation
could help identifying potential biases in the data,
including those arising from its geographical origin--
here, North American hospitals-- underrepresented populations,
and their distinctive characteristics-- here,
low resource or rare diseases.
Let's now provide examples of instance-based explanations.
The model identifies key patterns
in the input data that align with learn patterns
from training.
We would like to receive explanations
that focus on specific features that lead
to a particular prediction.
For example, a feature analysis explanation
could connect pneumonia with increased opacity
in the lower left lung region of the chest X-ray
and the shape and distribution of these opacities.
With this explanation, we understand
what are the features that played a significant role
in the pneumonia prediction for this specific patient.
Comparative explanations analyze the predictions
for different instances.
This explanation compares two instances, A and B,
highlighting the differences between them.
It helps users see why two cases are treated differently.
Here, we see that instance A is classified as a normal heart
rhythm, while instance B is classified
as atrial fibrillation due to the analysis of their ECGs.
The irregular RR intervals and the absence of distinct P waves
in instance B are supposed to--
the regular sinus rhythm and clearly defined P waves,
in instance A, are responsible for the different predictions.
A comparative explanation focuses
on different predictions for the same instance,
depending on its features.
Instead of comparing two different instances,
this method explains why a specific case was classified
as one label, P, instead of another,
Q. Brain MRI scan indicates a benign tumor, B, rather than
malignant cancer, Q, because the detected lesion in well-defined,
non-invasive, and does not exhibit irregular borders
or rapid growth characteristics.
Another interesting explanation is counterfactual.
Counterfactual explanations describe
what changes in input data would have
led to a different prediction.
My prediction is no pneumonia, but if the opacity in the lower
lung field were larger and more consolidated
or if C-reactive protein, CRP, levels increased,
I would predict pneumonia instead.