INSTRUCTOR: So the second example I would like to discuss
is related to the US criminal justice system.
So the United States has the highest incarceration rate
in the world, about 0.7% of the population, which
is a very significant number.
But unfortunately, incarceration rates
are not uniform across racial groups, as the graphs indicate.
So, a key aspect is recidivism.
So recidivism is the idea that people
who have been in the jail system and leave the jail system
commit crimes again and come back to the jail system.
So recidivism prediction instruments, RPI for short,
is the assessment of recidivism likelihood
are guiding pretrial release and parole decisions.
There is a particular organization, Northpointe,
it was founded in 1989, to develop software
for justice, as they call it.
And a particular system called COMPAS--
this is the Corrections Offender Management Profiling
for Alternative Sanctions, makes the recidivism prediction
from about 137 questions.
So an organization called ProPublicas, based on this data
set, try to assess whether such software systems are biased
or not.
The particular data set that they used was 7,918 criminal
defendants in a particular county in Florida in 2013
and 2014, and the recidivism outcomes through 2016.
In other words, this decision was taken in 2013-14,
and then we observe over the next two or three years whether
there was recidivism or not.
So the outcome variable is the risk score, low or high,
how likely it is the person would exhibit recidivism.
The variables, the independent variables,
were gender, age, race, as well as criminal history,
the date of the offense, the number of prior counts, the type
of previous offense, the history of revivalism,
the felony history, and how long the person has been in prison.
You observe the distribution of the COMPAS scores.
You observe that there are skewed to the left.
And you observe also that the incidence of recidivism
is close to 50%, which is a pretty significant number.
And you also observe that there is prevalence of recidivism
by race.
So you observe, for example, that the percentage
of Black people that exhibit recidivism
is higher than all others, all other races.
And then you also observe, similar to what
we have done for the low case, you
look at the distribution of covariates by group.
You look at the distribution of age, prior counts,
as well as the decile score for defendants
who have been assigned a high score by race and gender.
We observe that these data have, indeed, alpha bias.
The alpha for age is 0.29 and the alpha for gender is 0.12.
This means, again, that the percentage
of people who exhibit the recidivism
over the white population minus a corresponding percentage
of the Black population, this difference is 29%.
In other words, higher percentage of Black people
by about 29%.
And similarly for gender, although less, it's only 12%,
males are more likely than females to exhibit recidivism.
When we apply the same method, the mixed-integer optimization
and so forth, to flip, we also find
an area under the curve of 0.72 is exactly
the same methodology as before.
You observe the classification tree here with epsilon
equals 1%.
And we observe that the key variables,
of which to go left or right in the tree,
is race, age, as well as prior counts.
So, similar ideas, in other words,
that the logistic regression model identifies criteria
based on age and prior counts to select
the most qualified dependents among the Black population.
In particular, whenever the age is
above 36.5 and the prior counts is less than or equal to 3.
And these people, Black people, were assigned a negative label,
meaning parole was not given.
And we flip, this is the case, they now have a positive label.
And similarly, the model also identifies
criteria for the least qualified defendants
among the white subpopulation, and the criteria
the model used is that the age is less than 36.5
and the prior count is at least 1, or the age is less than 26.5,
and the prior counts also are less than 1.
These are defendants-- white defendants
who are assigned a positive label,
and we flip to a negative label.
Similarly, the leaf nodes that predict no change involve
the most qualified Black population in which we maintain
no change, and similarly, the least qualified,
we also exhibit no change, and similarly
for the white subpopulation.
This analysis is analogous to what
we have done in the law data set,
and it provides insights in which conditions under what
scenarios we flip the labels or not.
So if you take a moment and look at the key takeaways
of the lecture, we have observed that data sets exhibit bias--
in this particular case, very significant racial bias on two
examples.
So problems involving such individual choices
can be automated using machine learning algorithms--
this is what we have demonstrated--
that can alleviate individual biases
and enhance diversity without significantly compromising
on meritocracy.
In practice, the price of diversity can be quantified,
and consequently, the demographic parity
can be tuned to the level which is
appropriate for the problem at hand.
So this whole area shows the flexibility
that the techniques we have seen throughout universal AI,
namely machine learning and optimization,
can be flexibly adapted to improve diversity
with decreasing meritocracy only very slightly.