INSTRUCTOR: In this lecture,
we explore ideas and methods of symbolic AI,
a field of great theoretical and practical impact.
Symbolic AI is one of the two foundational pillars
of AI development.
It is not the primary driver of today's AI popularity,
as the other foundational pillar, machine learning,
in particular generative models, has delivered
the most impressive results.
On the other hand, it offers necessary solutions
to practical problems, especially
those related to model data representation and management.
Additionally, symbolic AI is the best way
to address many important issues related to the development
and use of trustworthy AI.
So it is nowadays a part of most compound AI systems,
like the LLM-based systems that we use every day.
In this lecture, we will explore modern symbolic AI methods
focusing on semantic data and knowledge representation,
management, and analysis.
In particular, we will present knowledge graphs,
the most efficient methods for data and knowledge
representation and sharing on the web.
They enable shared understanding of domain knowledge
between humans and machines.
In this context, we study the problem
of automated reasoning of developing algorithms and tools
for drawing conclusions from data and knowledge.
We focus on methods that scale, presenting their usefulness
and challenges related to the importance
and difficulty of the problem of reasoning as a mental process.
In most AI applications, it is necessary to describe
the knowledge about the domain and the relevant data
that we use.
This description must be useful for the AI services we develop.
But at the same time, it must be understandable by humans.
This is crucial in applications where domain experts
are involved in the process, defining
the terminology and the rules governing the field.
In practice, this knowledge is typically
represented using symbolic AI in the form of ontologies,
knowledge graphs, or if-then rules.
The goal is to represent knowledge
that is technically sound for AI agents
but also intuitive, understandable by humans.
Obviously, we cannot represent all relevant knowledge
or collect all useful data for the application of interest.
Usually, we have to accept that both our knowledge
and relevant data are incomplete.
One reason for incompleteness is that there
are important implicit facts or rules beyond what is explicitly
stated.
These facts and rules are crucial for the performance
of AI systems.
In such cases, humans use logic to derive conclusions
from existing knowledge through processes
that consistently lead to reliable and accurate outcomes.
This cognitive process is known as reasoning.
Symbolic AI provides technologies that
emulate this human capability.
This technology is known as automated reasoning.
With automated reasoning, we can automatically
detect knowledge inconsistencies or make implicit knowledge
explicit and, most importantly, offering
guarantees for the correctness and completeness of the methods.
Through the web, we can access vast amounts
of relevant, up-to-date information.
Without this information, AI systems
appear outdated and lose a significant part
of their credibility.
Retrieving information from heterogeneous data sources
is a challenging problem.
To solve it effectively, automated systems
must somehow understand the meaning of the search,
going beyond simple string matching.
Symbolic AI provides methods for retrieving relevant data
by leveraging formal domain knowledge descriptions.
These methods set a new level of effectiveness and efficiency
in information retrieval.
Any AI system used in high-risk applications
must offer clear, intuitive explanations of its functioning.
This is the most important aspect
of transparent AI that is necessary for the use of AI,
particularly in high-risk applications like health care.
The symbolic AI technologies mentioned earlier
are highly beneficial in this regard.
Specifically, by using formal knowledge representation
and reasoning, we can analyze the operation of AI systems,
extracting functioning rules that
are understandable to humans.
At the same time, we can ensure compliance
with recommendations or regulatory frameworks,
enhancing the credibility of AI.
Let's describe first some milestones
of the development of symbolic AI.
The foundations of symbolic AI are actually the foundations
of AI itself, as this is where the concepts developed
during the early stages of AI research.
In the '50s, Alan Turing introduced fundamental concepts
for machines that think like humans by following formal
procedures.
He also proposed methods to evaluate
whether a machine mimics human thought,
the well-known imitation game.
These ideas were later systematized
by numerous researchers and applied to problem-solving
using symbolic AI.
A milestone in this area was the general problem solver
developed by Newell, Simon, and Shaw,
utilizing formal mathematical logic to represent and solve
a wide range of problems.
In the following decades, particularly until the mid
'80s, knowledge-based and expert systems significantly developed
and applied in various domains.
Here, we have to mention the first attempts to formally
represent structured knowledge, the semantic networks,
and the first expert systems that were based on if-then rules
and used in medicine, chemistry, et cetera.
Perhaps the most important achievement in the area
was the development of automated reasoning algorithms, which
demonstrated both the potential and limitations
of algorithmic reasoning.
However, some of these findings contributed to the start
of the well-known AI winter of the '80s, which lasted more
or less until the rise of the web.
The web revolution facilitated the large-scale application
of machine learning technologies.
Moreover, the rise of the web also
sparked a revival of symbolic AI,
leading to modern symbolic AI engines.
Specifically, from the millennium,
symbolic AI systems evolved from standalone intelligence systems
to data-driven, web-based AI services.
A key milestone in this evolution
was the development of the Semantic Web.
Symbolic AI played a crucial role
in the semantic representation, retrieval,
and analysis of data and knowledge on the web.
Since 2000, the ideas and technologies
developed in the area have led to efficient management
and access of vast amounts of information,
primarily through the web.
This capability has contributed to the growth of massive data
sets as a catalyst to the rapid advancement of machine
learning, particularly deep learning,
which has become the driving force behind AI development.
On the other hand, the widespread adoption
of deep learning and AI, especially
after 2015 and its integration into numerous applications,
have also exposed critical challenges
that must be addressed to sustain this progress.
In this context, we see the emergence of complex AI systems
that integrate symbolic AI technologies with deep learning
models.
This integration can occur increasingly
through the development of neurosymbolic AI
or through hybrid approaches, such as compound AI, which
represent the next stage in AI development.
So the focus of modern symbolic AI
is to provide solutions for up-to-date information
retrieval, automation of LLM prompting, automated reasoning,
and the interpretation of deep learning models.
Data-intensive services are based
on the management and analysis of diverse data formats
from multiple sources.
For instance, this data can originate from physical devices
such as sensors that capture measurements
like biometric data, often in real-time.
Data may also include information
from public internet sources such as websites,
scientific data sets, and social media posts.
Additionally, data can be found in local databases
such as customer records, hospital patient data, and log
files, or internal data that include reports, analytics,
and user surveys.
Symbolic AI services can be used to gather, integrate, represent,
and manipulate relevant data.
Finding relevant data across numerous heterogeneous sources
is challenging.
To achieve this, an approach based on semantic understanding
should be used rather than traditional keyword-based search
methods.
To achieve this, domain-specific knowledge
should be formally represented in a way that is both human
and machine readable, enabling its use in data integration,
access, and analysis services.
Automated reasoning services enhance
these data-intensive systems by automatically drawing
conclusions from domain knowledge
and responding to user queries through the collection
and analysis of relevant data from multiple sources.