INSTRUCTOR: Another use of LLMs that people have been actually
doing a lot is medical QA.
This refers to the task of using AI, and more specifically
large language models, of course,
to answer medical questions.
And this can be simple or more complex.
In general, medical prompts can be unsafe.
The reason is that large language models are not
necessarily trained on very specific medical data.
So there is no guarantee that the output is actually
helpful and useful for the potential patient.
Here we're going to check a case, an example, where
we have this medical question.
What is the recommended chemotherapy dose
for a 45-year-old with stage III pancreatic cancer?
As we can see, Llama, this creates a fake example
of the patient, as in there is nowhere
information about the BMI or the creatinine level
or any of these.
Lama hallucinates here a lot.
It just finds some medical parameters that do not exist.
And it selects one of four options that it also generated.
So this is an example of a very bad response from Lama.
[? Openshot ?] has a better response here,
where basically it states that the recommended chemotherapy
would depend on several factors that include
patient's health, et cetera.
And it actually provides some--
a combination of chemotherapy, radiation therapy.
It actually provides information that is correct.
Medical QA is an area that one should
be very, very careful with when they use large language models.
We are also going to go over a case, another case,
probably, where we want to see how our models hallucinate
when they ask them to provide a citation for a fake paper.
So hallucination-- this is a term that we have mentioned
earlier in the recitation as well--
refers to when a model generates information that is false,
made up by the model, or not supported
by any external knowledge source or its training data.
But the model presents it with confidence, as if it were true.
So here, we are asking the models to provide a citation
for a paper with a title "Quantum Brain Networks
for Consciousness processing."
This paper does not exist.
So here, actually, Lama tells us that--
it basically says that it's not a real paper.
It wants to help us find more information
in this area, et cetera.
Lama did not fall in the trap, in a way.
However, [? Openshot ?] actually gave us
a fake, completely fake citation, a completely fake
paper that does not exist.
It states that this is published in the Journal Quantum
Information Processing.
It gives us some names of authors.
And it also gives us a link.
And it's kind of interesting because if we
click on the link, of course, the page is not found
because it is a fake link.
This was the case until recently, even with ChatGPT.
Of course, now, the reasoning models
have become way more powerful, and they can be
used for citation extraction.
But in the early stages of ChatGPT,
fake citations was something that you would
encounter very frequently.
So one should be very careful with cases like this.
We should always double check this type of information
before using it in any other context.
And I also wanted to show you an example of how ChatGPT can also
hallucinate.
This is, of course, the case.
But it can also hallucinate at a very basic level still.
So what we did was now, very, very recently,
we asked ChatGPT--
and this ChatGPT 4--
to give us the best paper of a certain researcher.
We have hidden the name here for privacy purposes.
But they are area researcher.
So we wrote this prompt.
Give me this person's best paper.
So actually, the model was able to find the correct citation,
which is this one here.
It is real.
It was actually published in 2004.
And it is also stated, which is true,
that this work has been cited well over 200 times
and remains a foundational study in the field.
It also provided a link to the specific publication.
It is important to note that although this was not
the most cited paper of the certain researcher, at least
it was real.
It was found by the model.
And it was accurate.
The next day, we asked exactly the same thing
with exactly the same prompt.
Give me this person's best paper.
And ChatGPT decided that it was not
able to locate any scholarly records for someone
with this name, which is, of course,
weird because just the previous day, ChatGPT gave us citations
for this specific scientist.
So this is to basically point out
that ChatGPT, although it's much better than these smaller models
that we saw, is actually not perfect.
And one might ask, since these models can be bad,
why would one still use them?
It is true that there are newer models with smaller size that
are constantly improving.
But it is important to still study these models,
because at the end of the day, we
want to have models with a few billion parameters that can run,
can be used with simpler and smaller GPUs,
instead of having to use huge models.
And if we want to use generative AI for our projects,
we will have to use small models, so efficient prompting
can make a difference.