INSTRUCTOR: This is all for the tabular part of this recitation.
And now we're moving on to image interpretability.
So as you might have seen in other modules as well,
deep learning models for images, like convolutional neural
networks, learn patterns, such as edges, textures, colors,
object, shapes.
But even though they're very accurate and efficient,
it is not always obvious why a CNN
makes a particular transaction.
And it's actually mostly not obvious.
So we are going to see here different methodologies that
have been developed that try to explain which
parts of the images are more important when we want
to predict a certain value.
So we're going to explore three different methods.
The first is saliency maps.
Saliency maps answer the question,
which pixels matter most?
So basically, they highlight the pixels of the original image
that the model is most sensitive to.
And how do we do that?
They basically work by computing the gradient of the model's
output with respect to each pixel.
And then, what does this show?
The gradient, if the gradient is high,
it means that we get a bright area in the saliency map.
And this means that small pixel changes strongly
affect the prediction.
So these pixels are important.
When the saliency map is dark, it
means that the gradient was small.
So it has little influence.
So basically, when the output of the model
has a high gradient with respect to a certain pixel,
it means that if this pixel changes by a little bit,
the output will still be significantly impacted.
And this means that this pixel is important.
Whereas, if the gradient is low, it
means that even larger changes in the pixel value
will not have such a big impact on the model output.
The second method is called LIME.
LIME stands for Local Interpretable Model-Agnostic
Explanations.
So basically, this can be also used for language,
and we are going to see that later in this recitation.
So that's what it means to be model agnostic.
It's not tailored to a certain architecture.
Basically, the idea-- and it's the same idea
that is also applied for language--
is that here for images, we break the image into what
we call super pixels that are small connected regions.
Think about it not as separate individual pixels
of the image but groups of connected small regions
of the connected pixels.
Next, we are randomly hiding or masking these regions,
and we are seeing how the prediction changes
when certain regions disappear.
And then we fit another surrogate model
to identify which regions were important.
So basically, we have a relationship
between the regions that we have hidden
and how the prediction changes.
So then we can use these hidden regions as input
and train a surrogate, a completely different model,
to learn which features led to the highest
changes in the output.
And in that way, we basically use a meta learner
to get some patterns of which hidden regions were
the most important and resulted in the biggest difference
when they were hidden.
It basically answers the question
if I remove this region, does the prediction
change significantly?
So this eventually produces an intuitive heatmap
of important image regions or areas of the regions
that end up being important.
The third method that we're going to explore
is called Grad-CAM.
This stands for Gradient-weighted Class
Activation Mapping.
And it is basically answering the question,
where does the CNN look?
So you don't need to know how CNN works.
But basically, what this does is that it
uses the final convolutional feature maps, which
means it uses some output of the intermediate outputs of the CNN
model, internal, let's say, quantize,
but towards the end of the architecture,
towards the output of the architecture.
And it also used their gradients to identify now
which spatial locations contribute most
to the predicted class and which regions the model
pays more attention to when making a decision.
So now we're not looking at individual pixels
like we did with the saliency maps,
but this is a bit different.
When we have bright red regions, we
have high importance, blue regions we have low importance.
But basically, the result is a localized heat map
that we overlay on the original image.
And this heat map tells us which parts the model
gave more attention to based on the final layers of the model
and their gradients.
So what we're going to do is that we're
going to use a pretrained large convolutional neural network.
It is trained on a specific data set,
and we are going to classify a dog image.
And after doing this classification,
we are going to explore the three interpretability methods
we talked about, saliency maps on individual pixels,
LIME score for meaningful regions,
and Grad-CAM for the model's high-level spatial attention.
And we're going to see which parts are considered important
based on each of these three methods
when the model made the prediction.
It's a single prediction, single model.
We're just trying to explain it using three different methods.
So we are loading the libraries that we
are going to use for this part.
We are loading the pretrained ResNet50 model here.
We load it from the torchvision library.
This is the model here.
And then the next thing is that we download the image
we are going to work on.
It's a publicly available image.
It's an image of a dog, as you can see.
We download it, and then we resize it
so that it's more manageable.
And the inference and everything happens fast.
So it's an easy image.
It's a dog.
It's easy to recognize.
We are going to define this preprocess pipeline here,
where we basically resize.
Here we resized for visualization purposes.
But we are resizing the image.
And notice that here we resized the NumPy version of the image.
The input to the preprocess pipeline
will be this version of the image
here that we loaded, that we haven't resized.
So that's why we are resizing it here.
It's not applied again, basically.
We transform it to tensor, which is important for the model.
And then we normalize it so that we
don't have very high values in our features.
These are all very standard in computer vision.
So we are preprocessing the image.
We're getting the tensor.
And then we are passing this image, this tensor,
through our pretrained ResNet model.
And at the end, we get the probabilities of the classes,
and we get the output probability.
We don't care if this is correct or not right now,
but the predicted class had number 258.
Now, let's see how we can calculate the saliency map.
So for this specific class that the model predicted,
what was the most important thing on the image that--
yeah, it was important for the model
to make the prediction according to the saliency maps.
We are basically taking the gradients here,
as we said earlier.
This is very simple.
It's just the back propagation gradient.
We are normalizing between 0 and 1.
And we are now going to show the resized image, the saliency map.
And then we can overlay the saliency map
on the image to see which parts light up,
which parts are brighter compared
to our exact initial image.
So what do we see?
We see that, actually, what was the most important
for the prediction was the shape of our dog.
See?
Here you can see the body of our dog on these red dots.
Red dots means that these had higher gradients,
so they were more important when we classified.
The background, the grass here, was not
important for this classification
to be made by the model.
And here in the overlay, you can see
how nicely the different regions of the dog bright up.
Now, moving on to the LIME explanation,
here we are loading the explainer.
We're creating the explainer.
We are going to basically use these LIME predict
function, where we take as input the images.
We preprocess them.
We have these batches of all the images.
And what happens is that basically--
yeah, all these images will be variations of the original image
when we hide different parts, when
we had different parts of the initial image.
That's why we have a for loop here.
That's why there are multiple images.
And then we get the probabilities
for all these different variations.
So this is how we use the-- we initialize the explainer,
use this explain instance function, which takes as input
the original image.
The LIME predict function, we are
taking the top label, the 258.
So that's what we're trying to explain.
We're taking the probabilities with respect to this.
And we also define how many samples we want it to generate.
So let's see.
After applying the LIME score, you
can see with yellow these closed regions here
that seem to be the most important.
And as you can see, these regions
focus on parts of the body of the dog, this part that
focuses on the tail.
There is this part that focuses on the body and the mouth.
And here we also have the eyes, the ear.
So again, we can see the parts of the dog
were the most important for making the classification, which
intuitively makes sense.
Finally, we're going to see the Grad-CAM interpretability
method.
We don't need to spend too much time on how the code works
exactly, but the idea is that we get the forward
and backward, basically, parts in some sense,
hooks-- we call it hooks-- of the target layer.
And then we take the activations and the grads and the weights,
and we compute, eventually, this final score.
And we can visualize it here.
That's all you need to remember.
We can visualize it.
And as we said, red regions correspond to high importance,
green to less, and blue to even less.
So as you can see, especially when
we overlay this map, that heatmap on our original image,
all this background, this dark blue, is not important at all.
Again, the silhouette of the dog seems to get the lighter blue.
And in the middle, we see that the highest importance
lies around here.
That's all for the images.
So we saw these three methods.
There's no good or bad method.
There's just different ways of trying
to explain which parts were the most important for the model.
And although the details, for example, this area here,
was not necessarily found by the other methods, the general idea
that the silhouette of the dog is the most important
for reaching the final class, it looks consistent
and makes sense.