INSTRUCTOR: Let's now examine how reasoning
is handled by both LLMs and symbolic AI reasoners.
We will compare the answer of ChatGPT
with the answer of basic automated reasoning
system for knowledge graphs.
Let's assume that both systems have only the example sentence
stored in their memory.
We will ask whether, based on this data,
it can be determined that La La Land is a love story.
For humans, this is straightforward,
as they understand that every romantic film, including
romantic musical films like La La Land, is a love story.
For a symbolic AI system to restrict
to the information of the sentence
is straightforward, as we can explicitly provide only
this knowledge as the input.
In an LLM, this process is more challenging,
if not extremely difficult.
First, we do not need to provide any input,
as the information from this text
is already encoded in the weights of the neural network.
It is reasonable to assume that the model has
been trained on Wikipedia data.
Also, the meaning of this information
is likely present in many publicly available texts that
were part of its training data.
However, it is difficult to ensure
that it knows only the elements of this sentence,
as LLMs inherently rely on vast amounts of pretrained data
beyond the given input.
To ensure the model relies only on this knowledge,
we use prompting, combining in-context learning
and role-playing techniques.
We contextualize the question within a game scenario,
explicitly instructing the model to only use
the given information to generate its response.
And then ask, is La La Land a love story?
The answer of ChatGPT is correct.
It is, "Based on the given information,
I can reasonably conclude that La La Land is a love story."
With a symbolic AI reasoning, the process is different.
We give only the statements included in the sentence
and some relevant rules.
And we directly input the question,
"Is La La Land a love story?"
And the response is correct--
yes.
Let's try to examine how reasoning
is performed in each system.
In the case of ChatGPT, its output
includes the reasoning process used to reach the conclusion.
It is clear that it recognizes the meaning of the sentence.
Moreover, it more or less follows the suggested game
scenario, as it restricts itself to using
only the information contained in the given sentence.
Finally, in the third step of reasoning,
ChatGPT appears to use additional domain knowledge,
specifically the information "a love story is a narrative
centered around romance."
That is relevant to the rule "romantic films are love
stories" that we provided to the symbolic AI reasoner.
On the other hand, the reasoning process of symbolic AI
is transparent, as it follows strict logical steps.
Initially, the fact "La La Land is a romantic musical film"
and the rule "romantic musical films are romantic films"
are combined to infer La La Land is a romantic film.
And this fact, combined with the rule "romantic films are love
stories," gives the conclusion La La Land is a love story.
That is the answer to the question.
So we understand that the symbolic AI reasoning
follows a transparent, rigorous algorithmic process, which
is good.
On the other hand, we must carefully select and provide
the symbolic AI reasoner with the relevant knowledge
in a formal language.
This is challenging.
With ChatGPT, the knowledge is already there,
encoded in the weights.
We don't have to give anything, which is good.
On the other hand, inside the system,
reasoning does not follow the step presented by ChatGPT.
The correct answer is based on complex statistical
associations, making the text of the answer to more likely follow
the prompt.
As a result, in more challenging reasoning problems,
we may encounter, by LLM reasoning, errors
that are difficult to trace.
Let's analyze a reasoning problem
where such issues arise to understand
that while LLM reasoning is easy to use,
it can sometimes be unreliable.
My company has two debtors--
Company A and Company B. We know that Company A
is a bankrupt company.
We don't know the bankrupt status of Company B.
Also, we know that Company B is the only debtor of Company A
and that Company B has only one debtor, Company C, that
is not a bankrupt company.
The question is, if my company has a debtor that
is a bankrupt company and this company has a debtor that is not
a bankrupt company, this becomes particularly relevant
if, for example, we need to determine
whether our company has a recourse to recover funds
from its bankrupt debtors.
The specific reasoning problem is difficult
because of the unknown status of company B.
The trick is that company B may be a bankrupt company or not.
If company B is not a bankrupt company,
then my company has a debtor that
is a bankrupt company, Company A, which
in turn has a debtor that is not a bankrupt company, Company B.
If company B is a bankrupt company,
then my company still has a debtor that is bankrupt--
Company B this time--
which in turn has a debtor which is not bankrupt,
Company C. So in all cases, the answer to my question is yes.
Let's examine how ChatGPT responds to this reasoning
problem.
First of all, it presents the problem statement
in a formal manner.
This description is a sound and complete description
of the problem.
Then it presents a step-by-step analysis
that seems like a goal-oriented reasoning strategy.
It seems rather intuitive and clear,
although it does not infer some new knowledge.
Then comes the answer part.
The first bullet captures the case
that Company B is not bankrupt, concluding that in this case,
the answer is yes.
This is right.
The second bullet captures the case that Company B is bankrupt.
And in this case, it notices that Company A does not
meet the criteria.
True but misses the fact that now Company B
meets the criteria.
As a result, the answer of ChatGPT is wrong,
connecting the positive answer with the bankrupt status
of Company B. This is a problem that
requires to be solved a challenging reasoning technique
known as conditional reasoning.
Unfortunately, many practical problems
involve conditional reasoning, as they often
contain unknown facts that require us to assume
whether they are true or not.
Let's now examine whether a symbolic AI
reasoner can effectively handle this problem.
The first step is to formally represent the knowledge.
The second step is to formally represent the question.
If we represent the knowledge as a knowledge graph,
the goal is to determine whether the available data allows
us to infer the existence of the hasDebtor
edge between my company and another node classified
as bankrupt with a nonbankrupt debtor.
Sophisticated automated reasoning algorithms
can effectively handle this problem.
They distinguish between two cases
to systematically evaluate it.
Let's examine this more closely.
In the first case, Company B is connected to the BankruptCompany
node, identifying that the desired
path exists within the knowledge graph in this case.
With this inference, it has concluded
that the answer to this question is yes
when Company B is bankrupt.
In the second case, Company B is connected
to the nonbankrupt company node.
And again, the desired path exists in the knowledge graph,
although this time it is different.
With this inference, it has concluded that in this case,
the answer to the question is also yes.
So in any case, the answer is yes.
Therefore, we see that symbolic AI reasoning can effectively
handle this case.
Indeed, automated reasoning algorithms
can effectively handle a wide range of reasoning problems,
under one condition.
The facts and rules describing the domain and the problem
should be formally and precisely formulated.
This is a challenging task in itself,
which must be undertaken only if guarantees related to reasoning
is a requirement of the specific AI application.
So we need to use symbolic AI reasoners.