INSTRUCTOR: When integrating AI models,
many services that involve humans in the monolithic AI
approach should be automated.
One of these technologies is search and data retrieval.
It is extremely useful, particularly in scenarios
of prompt enhancement and expansion
during prompt engineering.
When prompting LLMs, up-to-date data and knowledge
are essential.
Instead of relying solely on static pre-trained models,
AI components should be able to dynamically fetch and integrate
knowledge in real time.
The data accessible to semantic search and retrieval services
varies depending on the specific application
and its requirements.
They can originate from physical devices, such as sensors,
which capture and record information
about users or the environment.
For example, data related to the user's location obtained
from GPS can significantly improve
searches that are relevant to local information.
They also have access to public data sources via the web,
such as websites, social media posts, scientific data,
et cetera.
For example, data from recent social media conversations
can update the context of a prompt
with data that has not been used during the training of an LLM.
Local databases can also include relevant information
such as customer records, patient data, transaction logs,
and system log files.
For example, a patient's medical record
is crucial for establishing the relevant data
framework in the AI-assisted medical diagnosis process.
Proprietary data is also valuable,
including internal reports, legal documents,
strategic analysis, analytics, user surveys,
and other confidential information.
For example, user questionnaires are
useful for developing examples during the process of automating
systems design using LLMs.
Finally, in many cases, domain-specific knowledge
is essential, often recorded in ontologies, rules or knowledge
graphs to provide structured knowledge.
For example, automated reasoning systems
need to respond based on the updated rules that
constitute domain knowledge.
Knowledge graph embeddings capturing domain knowledge
are utilized to update and enrich information
during the prompt engineering process.
The process of accessing data using search
should be online, generating the queries in real time.
The queries are generated automatically, sometimes
leveraging terminological knowledge
to ensure precise and relevant information retrieval.
Moreover, relevant terminological knowledge
is accessed based on the context facilitating prompt engineering.
The ultimate goal of this process
is to collect relevant data and knowledge
and integrate it into the tasks performed by the AI system.