INSTRUCTOR: In this lecture, we'll discuss fairness and bias
in machine learning.
The problem we will be addressing
is the problem of systemic bias.
Systemic bias with respect to gender, race, and ethnicity,
often unconscious, but is prevalent in data sets involving
choices made by people.
Some examples include data sets related
to human choices like college admissions, hiring, lending,
or parole decisions that discriminate
against African-Americans or women.
Let me discuss the definitions of diversity and meritocracy
that is relevant in this lecture.
Diversity is defined as the practice of including people
from a range of different social and ethnic backgrounds,
and of different genders and sexual orientation.
Meritocracy is defined as the practice
of selecting people when a choice is made based
on achievement, as opposed to wealth or membership
in a special social class.
Often in practice, these two goals are in conflict,
and we observe an inherent trade-off between them.
Society has found it challenging to alleviate such bias
and achieve diversity in a way that maintains meritocracy
in these settings.
In recent years, due to the growing volume of applications
in college admission, hiring, lending, et cetera,
machine learning models are being increasingly employed
for such classification problems.
It has been shown that without appropriate intervention
during training or evaluation, classification models
train on such data sets can be biased against certain groups
of individuals.
Of course, we can apply simple remedies, for example,
ignoring the protected attributes, for example, gender,
race, ethnicity, et cetera.
But such practices are largely ineffective
due to the other factors being correlated with the protected
attributes.
The data can be inherently biased in possibly complex ways,
thus making it difficult to alleviate bias.
Of course, there is price on inaction.
Classification models that are actively trained on such data
sets become more biased over time
through feedback loops, wherein the bias
against a certain subpopulation can be amplified.
Feedback loops have been observed in predictive policing,
for example, credit markets, or many other applications.
Let me give you an example of the notion
of feedback loop in the context of predictive policing.
So whenever we encounter more crimes and arrests
in a particular neighborhood, this
results in an update of the crime database.
And of course, based on this updated database,
we train a predictive model.
This results in deploying more law enforcement resources
in these certain neighborhoods.
This means that there is an encounter more
crimes and arrests in these neighborhoods,
and the feedback loop continues.
Let me illustrate what we'll do today
using a data set involving law students.
This data set examines whether the bar exam taken
by law students in the United States
is biased against ethnic minorities, especially
Black students.
The data set also contains anonymized historical
information, including age, LSAT scores, law school GPA,
and undergraduate GPA.
To mathematize the information we'll present,
I'm going to use the following notation
that each of the students is assigned an outcome, minus 1
or plus 1, representing passing, plus 1, or failing, minus 1,
of the bar exam taken by the student.
We define the set w to be the set of white students, the set
capital B to be the set of Black students,
and then we denote by nw, the total number of white students
that have taken the exam, and b, the total number
of Black students who have taken the exam,
pw is the total number of white students
who have passed the exam, and pb,
the total number of Black students
who have passed the exam.
So we need to define what does it mean
to for a data set to be biased.
We utilize the notion of alpha bias,
alpha is a number between 0 and 1.
So we call a data set to be alpha
biased if the difference between the rates
of positive observation among the group of white students
and the group of Black students is at least alpha.
In other words, the percentage of white students
that have passed the exam minus the percentage of Black students
that have passed the exam, this difference is above a threshold
alpha.
In that case, the data set is alpha biased.
For example, if it's, let's say, 50%,
it means that the percentages are 50% apart,
an undesirable effect.
Let me define the notion of demographic parity.
So demographic parity of a classifier,
this is a system that decides who gets a positive outcome,
passes the bar exam, versus does not pass.
The definition is as follows.
If you take the percentage of white people who
pass the exam based on this classifier,
minus the percentage of Black people
who pass the exam based on this classifier,
this difference, the absolute value,
is less than some value epsilon, let's say, 1%, epsilon
equals 0.01.
In that case, we have parity, which is a desirable outcome
so that we have some notion of fairness.
So let me give you an example of such demographic parity.
Let's say we have two subpopulations,
subpopulation A and subpopulation B.
On the top left, we see that, out of 6 people,
4 had a positive outcome, passed the exam,
whereas on the subgroup B, out of the 6, 2 pass the exam.
So in this case, the data set is alpha equals 1/3 bias, so 1/3,
the difference is 4/6 minus 2/6, that's 1/3.
And then on the right, we see 3 out of 6
on the subgroup A who passed the exam, and 3 out of 6
on subgroup B that pass the exam.
So in this case, alpha equals 0.
That is demographic parity.
So now let me go into the key proposed solution.
So what we do is we allow to flip the outcome
labels while training the model to achieve parity.
And in particular, we're going to use optimization
to flip in an optimal way.
So we propose a mixed integer optimization
of the type you have seen in the area of prescriptive AI.
So we used mixed integer optimization, MIO,
for short, that introduces a variable Zi, 0 or 1,
to decide which outcome label to flip.
For example, a particular student
who was originally assigned plus 1, meaning passed the exam.
And if Zi equals 1, we flip.
So this Yi become minus 1.
And similarly, if Yi was minus 1, it did not pass the exam
and we flip, we make it Yi plus 1,
meaning the person passed the exam.
So if we decide to flip the outcome label of the ith
observation of the ith student, so the new, Yi, let's call it
Yí, the new Yi, is equal to Yi times 1 minus 2 times Zi.
In other words, if Zi is 0, we don't flip.
Then the new Yi is equal to Yi, we then flip it.
If, on the other hand, Zi is 1, 1 minus 2 Zi is minus 1.
So then Yí becomes minus Yi, therefore, we flipped it.
So of course, we need to be careful
how many variables we flip.
So we define the set of variables Zi
so that we only flip a portion.
We call it Tw of labels to flip among the white population,
and T subscript b proportion of labels
we flip in the b population, in the Black population.
And in order to achieve demographic parity at the level
epsilon, recall that this is the number of people
who pass the exam among the white population
minus the percentage of people who
pass the exam in the Black population,
this difference would be less than epsilon.
So we select Tw and Tb correctly,
as shown in the calculation.
Then we achieve epsilon demographic parity
if we flip Tw and Tb labels.