INSTRUCTOR: Turning our attention to post-hoc interpretation,
particularly to global explanation methods,
let's explore one of the most interesting methods,
the interpretable surrogate models.
A global explanation helps us understand the general decision
rules the model follows, how different features influence
predictions, whether the model exhibits systematic biases
or relies too heavily on specific features.
For example, consider a classification model
where we analyze how it makes predictions.
A global explanation might reveal
I classify instances as category X when feature A is high
and feature B is low.
However, when feature A is moderate but feature C is high,
I classify instances as category Y.
This tells us the general decision
structure the model follows, making it easier to verbalize
and therefore validate.
Another aspect of global explanations
is identifying which features drive the model's decisions.
For instance, overall, my predictions
are most influenced by feature A,
feature B, and feature C. Feature A contributes
to 40% of the decisions, feature B to 30%, and feature C to 20%.
Other features have minimal impact.
This insight allows us to detect potential biases.
If the model disproportionately relies on a specific feature,
it might indicate bias or overfitting.
A widely used technique for globally explaining complex AI
models is mimicking the black box model
using an interpretable surrogate model.
Deep neural networks and other black box models
often make highly accurate predictions.
But their internal decision-making process
is opaque.
To make these models more interpretable,
we can approximate their behavior
with a simpler, interpretable surrogate model,
such as a decision tree.
How does this work?
First, we train a complex model, such as a deep neural network,
on the original data set.
We then use the trained black box
model to predict outputs for a large set of instances.
Instead of using the original data set labels,
we train an interpretable model, such as a decision tree,
to mimic the black box model's predictions.
Since decision trees are intrinsically interpretable,
we can extract decision rules, feature-important scores,
and decision paths to approximate the black box
model's behavior.
Now let's explore how we can leverage surrogate models
for local interpretation.
Local interpretation aims to explain
why a specific instance was given a particular transaction
by an AI model.
Unlike global explanations, which
describe the overall behavior of a model,
local explanations answer the question,
why did the model make this specific prediction
for this particular input?
By analyzing individual decisions,
we can understand what features influenced the outcome.
Imagine a machine learning model is used
to evaluate loan applications.
A local explanation might provide insights
like the loan was rejected mainly
because of the applicant's low credit score
and high debt-to-income ratio.
The part-time employment status also negatively impacted
the decision.
This breakdown highlights the most important
contributing factors, making it easier
for the applicant and financial regulators
to understand the decision.
One very interesting and widely used
method for extracting post-hoc local explanations is LIME.
The acronym comes for local interpretable model
agnostic explanations.
LIME follows a four-step methodology.
First, we generate multiple slightly modified versions
of the original instance by introducing small changes
to its features, then each perturbed instance
is passed through the black box models
to record the changes in its output.
Once we do this, using the perturbed samples
and their predictions, we fit a simple interpretable model,
for example, a linear regression or a small decision tree.
And finally, we extract explanations
for the operation of the surrogate model,
hoping that this allows us to explain why the black box
model made its decision for this instance.
Considering the example of the deep neural network classifier
that recognizes tigers, we can use deep neural network
inference to generate perturbed instances
and use them to record the prediction changes.
Then we can find surrogate models by fitting interpretable
models like decision trees.
Using the important features-- for instance, large, golden,
yellow, or amber-colored eyes with round pupils,
small rounded ears, bold black stripes on an orange coat,
muscular body, long and striped tail--
we can extract explanations like instance
A was classified as a tiger because it
has bold black stripes on an orange coat, a muscular body,
a long and striped tail, small rounded ears,
large golden yellow or amber-colored eyes with round
pupils that involve these features.
Now let's discuss counterfactual explanations,
a powerful technique for understanding
AI decisions by exploring what could have been different.
What are counterfactual explanations?
Rather than explaining why an AI model made
the specific decision, counterfactuals
explai what minimal changes to the input
would have led to a different outcome.
Instead of answering, Why was my loan rejected?
a counterfactual explanation answers,
What would need to change for my loan to be approved?
Suppose an AI model rejects a loan application.
A counterfactual explanation might
say, if your credit score and your income
increased a bit, giving some numbers,
your loan would be approved.
This explanation provides actionable insight
into what the applicant can do to improve
their chances of approval.
Counterfactuals also apply to computer vision models.
Suppose an AI system classifies a domestic cat
as a tiger because of its background.
A counterfactual explanation might
say, if the same cat were in a living room,
the model would classify it as a domestic cat instead of a tiger.
This means that changing the background
alters the classification outcome.
In this case, counterfactuals explain
how context influences model decisions,
helping us detect possible biases in AI predictions.
To generate counterfactual explanations,
we can use several methodologies.
For example, there are optimization-based approaches.
The goal is to find the smallest possible change
in input features that would result
in a different prediction.
This is often done by solving an optimization problem where
we minimize the changes required to flip the model's decision.
For instance, instead of suggesting a major salary
increase, the model identifies that a 5,000 increase in income
and a 50 point increase in credit score are sufficient
for loan approval.
These methods ensure counterfactuals remain realistic
and minimally disruptive.
Another approach is to extract prototypes.
Instead of modifying the original instance,
this method finds a real-world example
from a different class that is similar to the given instance.
Generative models, such as GANs or variational autoencoders,
can be used to generate realistic counterfactual
instances.
For example, if a patient is diagnosed with a disease,
the system could find a similar patient
who was classified as healthy, highlighting the key differences
in their medical profiles.
This method helps answer, What does
a real example from the desired class look like?
making counterfactuals more interpretable.
So what is the take-home message of this lecture?
First of all, AI is very useful, but there
are many considerations to be taken into account.
In particular, potential risks that
may be material or immaterial, stemming from biased decision
making, unfair treatment, security vulnerability, and AI
system malfunction, among others.
The lack of transparency in AI models
contributes to algorithmic aversion,
where users are reluctant to trust automated decisions.
Without clear explanations, AI remains a black box,
making it harder for users to trust AI and adopt it
in practice.
Explanations are key to AI transparency.
To build trustworthy AI, we need transparent and interpretable
systems.
This means that we need to extract explanations that
describe the AI model predictions,
but also the data collection, pre-processing,
and training processes.
To trust the AI system, users should
be able to understand how a specific instance was classified
and what factors influenced the outcome.
On the other hand, providing explanations
is not an easy task.
While the need for explainability is clear,
implementing effective explanations
remains a major challenge.
Context is crucial to understand explanations terminology,
and the form of explanation is important.
Different applications require different types of explanations.
For example, a doctor may need a description of the detailed AI
reasoning in medical terms, while a loan applicant may
need a simple and intuitive justification
for the rejection of an application
or the factors that should be changed for getting acceptance.
And finally, it is very challenging
to develop interpretable machine learning models
with high accuracy as it is to successfully post-hoc interpret
black box AI models like deep neural networks.
By addressing these challenges, we
can build trust moving forward to a more human-centered AI.
Thank you for your attention.