INSTRUCTOR: To recap, after examining issues related
to AI system components in multi-component architectures,
let's now describe some key challenges that
emerge from the integration of these components.
There are major design challenges to address.
There are numerous architectural choices.
Identifying the optimal design is a complex problem
that is expected to be systematically addressed
in the coming years.
Moreover, while optimization challenges for individual AI
models are well understood, optimization and training
of a system integrating multiple AI models
is a new and complex problem.
On the other hand, there are great opportunities.
For example, an AI system can enhance efficiency
by leveraging multiple smaller, specialized models tailored
to specific tasks rather than relying
on a single large model that demands significant resources.
Finally, new challenges arise in the integration of AI models,
particularly as they are resource-demanding and evolve
rapidly.
For practical deployment, processes such as monitoring
and orchestration should be automated,
and data pipelines should be carefully defined.
Security, reliability, accountability,
and interpretability challenges should
be addressed, especially when integrating powerful AI
systems that automatically retrieve and utilize information
from the web.
So what is the take-home message of this lecture?
First, monolithic AI systems can solve many problems,
but the growing demands on AI have made it clear
that only a combination of AI models
can fully meet modern requirements.
This is what many AI systems are doing today
to improve their performance.
For example, RAG systems combine advanced retrieval with LLMs.
Modern commercial LLMs integrate multi-modal capabilities--
for example, image analysis-- or symbolic AI--
for example, symbolic math engines--
to enhance their functionality.
There are now many techniques and approaches
available to automate the prompting process.
Prompts can be very sophisticated,
integrating elements from other systems such as search
and retrieval, knowledge graphs, and reasoning services.
Prompt engineering improves LLM's responses.
Many essential features of AI systems depend on reasoning.
For example, in domains such as health care, finance, and law,
AI systems must ensure explainability.
We can leverage the reasoning capabilities of symbolic AI
systems or LLMs depending on the specific application
requirements.
Combining different AI models can
tackle more complex problems, but it also
introduces new challenges that we have not previously
encountered.
For example, optimization at the system level rather than
the model level demands entirely new approaches.
Moreover, security challenges arising
from the integration of retrieval engines in LLMs
introduce new risks, particularly concerning
personal data protection.
As we have seen in recent years, the future of AI
extends beyond monolithic systems,
making it crucial to address these emerging challenges.
Thanks for watching.