INSTRUCTOR: The explanations presented
earlier represent ideal scenarios
of how AI systems should justify their predictions.
The reality is that machine learning
based AI systems, especially the most accurate ones,
do not inherently operate within such
a structured symbolic knowledge framework.
Most successful AI models, like deep learning systems,
operate by identifying statistical complex patterns
in data rather than applying explicit symbolic reasoning.
While AI can provide highly accurate predictions,
it often lacks the ability to articulate the reasons
behind these predictions in a manner that aligns
with human-like reasoning.
This limitation makes it difficult to extract
explanations that are meaningful to humans,
because AI models don't inherently comprehend concepts
in the same way humans do.
So post-hoc interpretations of AI models can be challenging.
Rather than revealing the actual reasoning process
behind the prediction, models often
provide general justifications that
make the decision appear valid.
Consequently, post-hoc explanations
may not accurately reflect the exact thought process
that led to an AI prediction.
Let's illustrate this concept with a simple example.
Imagine an AI system trained to classify images of animals.
Its training data, data set D, includes
images of various animals like tigers and domestic cats.
During the training phase, the parameters of a predictor H
are adjusted to accurately classify
the images in the data set.
The goal is to achieve generalization.
Remember, this means ensuring that the model correctly
labels unseen animal images while avoiding overfitting.
During the inference phase, the predictor
processes unseen images and assigns
them a label, for example, tiger or domestic cat.
Of course, labeling can be challenging,
as some animal images may be more difficult to classify
than others.
Since a human can often identify key features or patterns
at a glance and label an image as a tiger,
a question arises, can we semantically explain
how we recognize these features or patterns?
Can we describe the cognitive process
behind this identification and labeling?
And most importantly, what technical requirements
would be necessary for the predictor
to achieve a similar level of explainability?
Addressing these questions is crucial to ensure that AI models
not only accurately classify data, but also
provide the real explanations and reasoning
behind their prediction.
Providing semantic explanations for labeling an image
as a tiger or a domestic cat requires
describing the typical characteristics
that distinguish these animals.
For example, distinguishing characteristics
could be visual, structural, and behavioral.
A tiger is typically characterized by its large size,
muscular build, orange fur with black stripes,
and distinctive facial markings.
In contrast, a domestic cat is significantly smaller,
has a more varied fur pattern, and has
different body proportions and facial structures.
By defining these features, we establish a context
for semantic explanations, enabling both humans and AI
models to articulate why a particular image belongs to one
category rather than another.
With a certain level of abstraction,
we can identify features that distinguish between categories,
even though some characteristics may overlap and create
similarities in appearance.
These features help in recognizing patterns that
are crucial for classification.
For instance, both tigers and certain domestic cats
may share striped fur patterns, but factors
like size, body proportions, facial structures, and muscle
build can help draw clearer distinctions.
While similarities do exist, focusing
on the most discriminative features
makes classification easier, whether performed
by humans or AI systems.
The table summarizes these features.
Explanations based on these features
can be highly informative.
For example, instance A was classified
as a tiger due to its bold black stripes, orange coat,
large muscular build, and broad face with small rounded ears.
Or instance B was classified as a domestic cat
due to its small body size, thinner build,
rounder eyes, narrow, irregular stripes, and long, thin tail.
Of course, there are also other contexts
in which explanation can be extracted,
referring to the different image backgrounds, a jungle setting
for a and an indoor environment for B.
And so the question is, in which context
is the predictors functioning most effectively described?
Shifting our focus to the human brain's recognition process,
it appears that humans rely on a complex interplay
of visual processing, memory, experience, and cognitive
reasoning to identify objects and entities.
Unlike symbolic reasoning, this process
is not entirely transparent or explicitly rule based.
Instead, recognition often occurs
intuitively and subconsciously, saved by learned patterns
and prior experience.
In borderline cases, ambiguous situations, or when explaining,
humans can engage in deliberate thinking and reasoning
to refine or describe their classification.
AI predictors, such as deep neural networks,
rely on nonlinear processes to make predictions.
Deep neural networks learn intricate patterns
from vast amounts of data, making
their decision-making process challenging to interpret.
Their predictions emerge through layered transformations
of input data and abstract features that may not always be
directly explainable to humans.
While their accuracy can be highly impressive,
the lack of transparent reasoning
poses challenges in understanding and validating
their decisions, necessitating post-hoc explanation techniques
to approximate their internal logic in human terms.
However, there is a risk in relying
on post-hoc explanations that approximate the internal logic
in human terms.
They may provide intuitive descriptions
that might not accurately reflect how the system actually
makes its predictions, especially
in the presence of bias.
Deep neural networks excel at detecting statistical patterns
within data sets.
If the training data contains bias,
the model may learn and reinforce these biases.
Explanations should not obscure this issue,
but instead highlight it.
Rather than simply justifying a prediction,
an explanation should help reveal
whether biases in the data influence the outcome.
Consider the following example.
An AI model is employed to help to approve or reject
loan applications by analyzing applicant data.
The system was trained on historical financial records
that contain biases.
In the past, applicants from specific neighborhoods
were denied loans due to systemic inequalities.
Suppose that an applicant from a historical underprivileged
neighborhood applies for a loan and is rejected
by the AI system that encodes the statistical relevance that
is a result of bias in this case.
A standard misleading explanation
could be the loan application was rejected
because the applicant's income and credit score did not
meet the required threshold, while the real reason
is the underprivileged neighborhood of the applicant.
In this case, the correct explanation
should be the applicant's residential area
is the significant factor for rejecting the loan application.