INSTRUCTOR: For the second part of this recitation,
we are going to focus on Retrieval-Augmented Generation,
which is a technique that combines
the power of Large Language Models with access
to real-world information.
The idea is that we don't want to only rely
on what the model has learned during training only,
but we also want to give access to the model
to a database or a document collection
to find relevant information that
can be used to generate a more accurate and grounded response.
This is especially useful for answering questions
in topics that require up-to-date facts,
domain-specific knowledge, or detailed context.
And they can be generally more niche.
This is because, of course, online content
does not cover every topic and every subject in much detail.
RAG retrieves the real document first
and focuses on the relevant information for the task
that we want to solve for the specific prompt
that we want to focus.
And then it generates answers based on them.
This helps reduce hallucinations and make the model's output
more reliable.
Before we move on to the code, I am
going to explain what the task that we want to do actually is.
The idea is that we have a patient with some symptoms.
And we want to ask our small LLMs,
Llama and OpenChat to make a suggested
diagnosis for this patient.
Now, we can do that and ask what they think the patient has,
which is relevant to what we did earlier.
Or we can also use some information
that we know is relevant in order to help the models provide
a better output.
So the idea is that we have a medical document,
which is called "Rare Conditions,"
we have loaded in the File sections here.
And this file is very big and its many pages long.
And it contains information about different rare cardiac
conditions.
And by information, I mean symptoms, diagnostic criteria,
treatment, et cetera, but it's very big.
The task that we want to solve is to diagnose this 34-year-old
woman who has sudden chest pain after recent childbirth and no
prior cardiac history.
Of course, we have made this prompt.
And we know that the condition that we have in mind
is spontaneous coronary artery dissection, which
is a very specific and rare condition that
is related to some complications after giving birth.
The important thing to note is that this condition is rare.
And there is a high chance that our LLMs will not
have been trained on many data regarding this condition.
But our Rare Conditions file contains information
about multiple rare conditions.
So we want to use, to leverage, the information in this file
to guide the diagnosis generation.
As I mentioned earlier, this file is very big.
So it contains information about many conditions
that might not be relevant for this specific patient case.
In order to solve this problem, the first part
of retrieval-augmented generation
is to use the information that is available
and to only detect the relevant parts of it.
How do we do that?
We do that using a model, which is in the family of sentence
transformers.
And this model will allow us to actually find
the most relevant parts to the query that we have in hand.
First, we are going to split the big text file of rare conditions
into smaller chunks.
And after we do that, we use the sentence transformer model,
the SBERT model to encode these chunks
and convert them to embeddings.
So after performing this, we have the big file split
into chunks, and we have a single embedding for each chunk.
Then we have our query, which refers to the patient case.
And we also pass this query through the same model
to get an embedding that summarizes
the information of the patient.
So now we have one query embedding
that corresponds to the patient, and multiple chunk embeddings
that correspond to the different chunks in which we have
split the original big text file with the rare cardiac
conditions.
Now, in order to find the most relevant information
for the task in hand, we want to find which of these chunk
embeddings are more similar to our query embedding,
because if these embeddings are more similar in the embedding
space, this means that the information that they encode,
the raw text that they encode is also going to be
more relevant and more similar.
So we calculate the cosine similarity
scores between the query embedding
and all of the chunk embeddings.
So we then keep the top-k.
In our case, we have selected the top five
chunks that are more similar according to the embedding
distances.
And we basically only retrieve the relevant chunks
that we can view here.
So you can see, we have five different chunks--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
And something that is good is that the first two actually
refer to the SCAD diagnosis that we had in mind
when we created this patient case.
So the SBERT was actually capable
of isolating the parts that seemed
more similar, more relevant, to this description of the patient.
The second, third, and fifth, of course,
they're related to cardiac conditions.
The whole file that we had was about cardiac conditions.
But they are not related to the specific condition.
It doesn't matter though.
This is the whole, whole text that we're going to use.
And we're going to include this in our prompt
when prompting Llama and OpenChat.
And we hope that they are going to use this information
to guide their diagnosis.
So here is the full prompt.
We are doing role instruction here.
So basically, we're telling the model
that it should respond as a clinical assistant.
We actually point out that we wanted
to focus on the specific patient case
and the retrieved medical information,
and give us an answer about the most likely diagnosis.
We also include this sentence-- and this is important,
we're going to discuss it in a few minutes--
that we only want the model to ground its responses
on the provided information regarding the patient case.
We don't want it to imagine any other information
that we haven't given to it.
So when we run our model--
and this is the prompt.
Here is where the Llama gave its output.
So we can see that based on the patient case,
the most likely diagnosis is actually
spontaneous coronary artery dissection, which
is the ground truth, which is what
we wanted the model to output.
And this is justified by the patient symptoms,
such as sudden chest pain after recent childbirth
and no prior cardiac history.
These are compliant with the SCAD condition, et cetera.
And there's a fully grounded explanation on that.
OpenChat did the same thing.
Based on the provided patient case,
the most likely diagnosis is spontaneous coronary artery
dissection.
And it describes SCAD patients often
do not fit the typical profile for coronary disease
and the symptoms.
And it explains why it doesn't think
that restrictive cardiomyopathy, which is another condition,
is the case here, et cetera.
So using the medical context that is provided,
both of the models were able to find the right diagnosis.
And I repeat, the whole pipeline involved
first finding the relevant chunks, the relevant information
from a document that contained a lot of information
about cardiac conditions, and then
using these in the prompt we gave to the large language
models to help them to guide their generation.
OK, now, that's a good thing, of course.
But what would have happened without the provided context,
without giving them any information
about this rare disease and just asking
them to make a diagnosis based on only
the description of the patient.
Llama actually diagnosed the patient
with acute coronary syndrome, which the symptoms are similar,
but it is not accurate, because acute coronary syndrome
is usually caused by some plaque that
is accumulated on the vessels.
And this is not the case with this specific patient.
Similarly, OpenChat gave the same diagnosis.
And it also gives a more detailed reasoning
about what ACS is, when it happens, et cetera.
But we know this is not the specific diagnosis
that we wanted the models to actually give.
So in this case, we show how important
it is to actually provide relevant information
in the form of this context, to guide the diagnosis
and to get more accurate text generation.
The thing that I want to point out before wrapping up is that
we included the sentence, "please only stick
on the provided information regarding the patient case,
and don't make any further assumptions about the patient"
in the prompt.
So even with the context and the retrieved medical information,
if we do not include this sentence,
the models are more prone to some form of hallucination.
So when we remove this sentence, although both of them
again made the right diagnosis, you
can see here that, for example, Llama
wrote that the fact that her arteries are clean of plaque,
this, although we know it's not the case,
it's not explicitly mentioned in the prompt that we gave.
So although, yeah, we suspect it is the case because we know
that this woman did not have a prior cardiac history, since it
is not explicitly mentioned, the model
should not use it as an argument for its reasoning
for its diagnosis.
So we need, even in these cases, to be very careful with how
we structure our prompt.