INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's recitation.
Today, we are going to talk about specific concepts
that you saw in one of this module's lecture,
and more specifically prompt engineering and retrieval
augmented generation.
This module has covered a wide range of topics,
but today we chose to talk about these specific ones,
because we think they are also more relevant for everyday
and real life practice.
So in this recitation, we are going
to explore how to interact with large language models
more effectively and in a more skeptical way.
We are going to do that through prompt engineering and retrieval
augmented generation.
We don't want to rely on a specific model
and assume that this model knows everything.
We want to critically approach the outputs of LLMs,
and we want to investigate how structured and smart prompts
and also external context can potentially
improve model responses.
So we are going to go over different types
of prompt structures and their impact on model performance.
We are going to investigate how smaller open source
LLMs or large language models compare
to ChatGPT in different prompting scenarios.
We are going to briefly go over the design and use of RAG,
or retrieval augmented generation pipelines,
to improve factual accuracy and reasoning.
So we hope that by the end of this recitation,
you are going to have a better understanding of how
to thoughtfully and critically approach the outputs of LLMs
and how to use specific prompt design and information
retrieval to have more reliable and controllable outputs.
First of all, we need to install some packages that are not
already available in Google Colab, the ones
that you can see here.
And we are noting that one of the models
that we are going to use today, LLaMA,
although it's publicly available,
it requires an access request from Hugging Face, where we
generally load our models from.
So what this means is that in order to be used,
we need to submit a form to Hugging Face
and then get access to it.
Of course, I have already done that, otherwise I wouldn't
be able to run the code.
But for any user, for any learner that is willing,
that wants to actually try this themselves, here
there are detailed instructions about how
to access Llama on Hugging Face in a step by step fashion.
Very briefly, first of all, you need
to create a Hugging Face account,
and this is the link to do that.
Then for some of the models on Hugging Face,
and specifically for the model we're going to use,
which is this LLaMA 3 model, it's called Meta LLaMA 38b
instruct, you will need to request access from Meta.
So you need to click on this expand
to review and access button.
There is a form that you will need
to fill with some of your personal information,
and then you will need to wait for approval.
It usually doesn't take long.
When you get an email that confirms that you are approved
to use this specific model, you will be actually
able to access the files.
In case you want to load these files in Google Colab,
like we're doing here, you will need to basically authenticate
through Google Colab.
So this is why you need to get a Hugging Face access
token in order to load the models programmatically,
and you can generate one token by visiting this link here.
As I mentioned, in order for me to be
able to use this model here, I actually had to run these lines.
And when you run this cell, you will
get a login prompt that asks you to basically input
your password.
And then after this is finished, you're all good,
you're authenticated, and you can actually
load the weights of the LLaMA model that you want.