<problem url_name="problem_cc9fc0bcef15df3e02f6ac70a38e296a">
  <choiceresponse>
    <label>You are shown the Random Forest feature importance table, where <code>oldpeak</code>, <code>thal_3</code>, and <code>cp_0</code> rank highest. Which of the following conclusions <b>cannot be justified </b>based on this table alone? (Select all that apply.)</label>
    <checkboxgroup>
      <choice correct="false"><code>oldpeak</code> is frequently used by the forest to split the data.</choice>
      <choice correct="true">Increasing <code>oldpeak</code> will increase the predicted risk of heart disease.</choice>
      <choice correct="false"><code>thal_3</code> plays a larger role than chol in the model’s overall predictions.</choice>
      <choice correct="true">For an individual patient, <code>thal_3</code> necessarily contributed more to the prediction than<code> chol</code>.</choice>
      <choice correct="false">The forest relies on nonlinear decision rules involving these features.</choice>
    </checkboxgroup>
  </choiceresponse>
  <solution>
    <div class="detailed-solution">
      <p>Explanation</p>
      <p>Random Forest feature importance summarizes how useful features are <b>across the entire ensemble</b>, typically by measuring how much they reduce impurity when used in splits. This allows us to conclude that highly ranked features are frequently and effectively used by the model and that some features play a larger global role than others. However, feature importance does <b>not</b> provide information about the <i>direction</i> of an effect (whether increasing a feature raises or lowers risk) and it does <b>not</b> explain individual predictions. For a specific patient, a globally important feature may not be used at all, while a less important one can dominate the decision path, because global importance provides no information about which features were actually used or how strongly they contributed to that patient’s route through the forest. Understanding directionality or patient-level influence requires different tools.</p>
    </div>
  </solution>
</problem>
