<problem url_name="problem_f8708b6c2c2dcd6fd47e038bea460700">
  <choiceresponse>
    <label>Two students are discussing the SHAP explanations for this specific patient, whose top local contributions are: <ul><li>Strong positive: <code>cp_0, ca_0, chol, thalach</code></li><li>Strong negative: <code>thal_3, oldpeak, thal_2, age, exang_0</code></li><li><b>Student 1:</b> “Since <code>cp_0</code> and <code>ca_0</code> are near the top of the global SHAP plot, they must fully explain why this patient has a predicted risk around 0.68.”</li><li><b>Student 2:</b> “Not quite. The local explanation shows that some globally important features <i>reduce</i> risk here, and others with mixed global behavior matter a lot for this patient.”</li></ul>Which statements best support <b>Student 2’s</b> interpretation? (Select all that apply.)</label>
    <checkboxgroup>
      <choice correct="true">Although <code>cp_0</code> is globally important, this patient’s prediction also depends heavily on features like <code>thal_3 </code>and <code>oldpeak</code>, which substantially lower risk locally.</choice>
      <choice correct="true">Features such as <code>chol</code> and <code>thalach</code> meaningfully increase this patient’s predicted risk even though they are not the top-ranked features globally.</choice>
      <choice correct="false">Because <code>cp_0</code> has the largest positive local contribution, it is the primary driver of the prediction and other features play only a minor role.</choice>
      <choice correct="true">The local explanation shows that this patient’s prediction reflects a balance of large positive and negative contributions from different clinical factors.</choice>
      <choice correct="false">Since <code>thal_3</code> reduces risk for this patient, it should generally be interpreted as a protective factor in the population.</choice>
    </checkboxgroup>
  </choiceresponse>
  <solution>
    <div class="detailed-solution">
      <p>Explanation</p>
      <p>The local contribution table shows that <code>cp_0</code> strongly increases this patient’s predicted risk, but it is <i>not acting alone</i>. Features such as <code>thal_3,</code> <code>oldpeak</code>, <code>thal_2</code>, and <code>age</code> have large negative contributions that push the prediction in the opposite direction. At the same time, features like <code>chol</code>, <code>ca_0</code>, and <code>thalach</code> add additional upward pressure on risk. This illustrates why global importance rankings are insufficient for explaining individual predictions. While global SHAP highlights which features matter most <i>on average</i>, the local explanation reveals how opposing clinical factors combine for this patient to produce the final probability. The prediction is therefore the result of a <b>balance of multiple influences</b>, not dominance by a single feature or a fixed global pattern.</p>
    </div>
  </solution>
</problem>
