<problem url_name="problem_a2f785a6bf638237ca0986caa83caeee">
  <choiceresponse>
    <label>Let’s focus on <code>cp_0</code>, <code>age</code> and <code>ca_0.</code> Which statements are supported by the RF importance table and the SHAP summery plot?  (Select all that apply.)</label>
    <checkboxgroup>
      <choice correct="true">SHAP allows you to see that higher <code>cp_0</code> values generally <i>lower</i> predicted risk, while RF importance alone cannot show this direction.</choice>
      <choice correct="false">From the RF importance table, you could infer that <code>ca_0</code> increases predicted risk more than <code>cp_0.</code></choice>
      <choice correct="true">SHAP shows that the effect of <code>age</code> varies across patients, while RF importance summarizes only average usage.</choice>
      <choice correct="false">Because <code>cp_0</code> ranks high in both methods, its effect must be linear and consistent across patients.</choice>
      <choice correct="true">SHAP provides information about both which features matter and how they influence predictions, while RF importance focuses only on how often features are used.</choice>
    </checkboxgroup>
  </choiceresponse>
  <solution>
    <div class="detailed-solution">
      <p>Explanation</p>
      <p>In the Random Forest importance table, <code>cp_0, age,</code> and <code>ca_0 </code>all rank relatively high, indicating that these features are frequently used by the forest to make informative splits. However, RF importance alone does not indicate <i>how</i> these features affect predictions. The SHAP summary plot adds this missing information. For <code>cp_0,</code> points corresponding to the active category tend to lie on the negative side of the plot, indicating that higher<code> cp_0 </code>values generally <i>lower</i> predicted risk in this model: something that cannot be inferred from RF importance. For <code>age</code>, SHAP values are spread on both sides of zero, showing that age can either increase or decrease predicted risk depending on the patient’s context. Finally, SHAP provides both a ranking of feature importance and insight into direction and variability of effects, whereas RF importance summarizes only overall usage across the ensemble.</p>
    </div>
  </solution>
</problem>
